<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2023 15:41:02 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Compositionality of planar perfect matchings</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.08767</link><description>We exhibit a strong connection between the matchgate formalism introduced by Valiant and the ZW-calculus of Coecke and Kissinger. This connection provides a natural compositional framework for matchgate theory as well as a direct combinatorial interpretation of the diagrams of ZW-calculus through the perfect matchings of their underlying graphs.   We identify a precise fragment of ZW-calculus, the planar W-calculus, that we prove to be complete and universal for matchgates, that are linear maps satisfying the matchgate identities. Computing scalars of the planar W-calculus corresponds to counting perfect matchings of planar graphs, and so can be carried in polynomial time using the FKT algorithm, making the planar W-calculus an efficiently simulable fragment of the ZW-calculus, in a similar way that the Clifford fragment is for ZX-calculus. This work opens new directions for the investigation of the combinatorial properties of ZW-calculus as well as the study of perfect matching counting through compositional diagrammatical technics.</description><author>Titouan Carette, Etienne Moutot, Thomas Perez and Renaud Vilmart</author><pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.08767</guid></item><item><title>Complete Graphical Language for Hermiticity-Preserving Superoperators</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.04212</link><description>Universal and complete graphical languages have been successfully designed for pure state quantum mechanics, corresponding to linear maps between Hilbert spaces, and mixed states quantum mechanics, corresponding to completely positive superoperators. In this paper, we go one step further and present a universal and complete graphical language for Hermiticity-preserving superoperators. Such a language opens the possibility of diagrammatic compositional investigations of antilinear transformations featured in various physical situations, such as the Choi-Jamiołkowski isomorphism, spin-flip, or entanglement witnesses. Our construction relies on an extension of the ZW-calculus exhibiting a normal form for Hermitian matrices.</description><author>Titouan Carette, Timothée Hoffreumon, Emile Larroque and Renaud Vilmart</author><pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.04212</guid></item><item><title>Cutting multi-control quantum gates with ZX calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.00387</link><description>Circuit cutting, the decomposition of a quantum circuit into independent partitions, has become a promising avenue towards experiments with larger quantum circuits in the noisy-intermediate scale quantum (NISQ) era. While previous work focused on cutting qubit wires or two-qubit gates, in this work we introduce a method for cutting multi-controlled Z gates. We construct a decomposition and prove the upper bound $\mathcalO(6^2K)$ on the associated sampling overhead, where $K$ is the number of cuts in the circuit. This bound is independent of the number of control qubits but can be further reduced to $\mathcalO(4.5^2K)$ for the special case of CCZ gates. Furthermore, we evaluate our proposal on IBM hardware and experimentally show noise resilience due to the strong reduction of CNOT gates in the cut circuits.</description><author>Christian Ufrecht, Maniraman Periyasamy, Sebastian Rietsch, Daniel D. Scherer, Axel Plinge and Christopher Mutschler</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.00387</guid></item><item><title>CSS code surgery as a universal construction</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2301.13738</link><description>We define code maps between Calderbank-Shor-Steane (CSS) codes using maps between chain complexes, and describe code surgery between such codes using a specific colimit in the category of chain complexes. As well as describing a surgery operation, this gives a general recipe for new codes. As an application we describe how to `merge' and `split' along a shared $øverlineX$ or $øverlineZ$ operator between arbitrary CSS codes in a fault-tolerant manner, so long as the participating qubits satisfy a technical condition related to gauge fixing. We prove that such merges and splits on LDPC codes yield codes which are themselves LDPC.</description><author>Alexander Cowtan and Simon Burton</author><pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2301.13738</guid></item><item><title>Towards a Curry-Howard Correspondence for Quantum Computation</title><link>https://theses.hal.science/tel-03959403/document</link><description>In this thesis, we are interested in the development of a Curry-Howard correspondence for quantum computing, allowing to represent quantum types and quantum control-flow. In the standard model of Quantum Computation, a classical computer is linked to a quantum coprocessor. The classical computer can then send instructions to allocate, update, or read quantum registers. The programs executed by the coprocessor are represented by a quantum circuit: a sequence of instructions that applies unitary operations to the input quantum bits. While the model is universal, in the sense that it can represent any unitary operations, it stays limited: it lacks of proper representation of non-causal execution flow. Normally, to represent branching, one can use a type system featuring a coproduct, allowing for the choice between two possible executions, but quantum circuits only feature qubits and tensors thereof. On the other hand, types and strongly related to logic via the Curry-Howard correspondence which states that types of programs correspond to formulas and programs to proofs, while the program evaluation is matched with the proof simplification. While this correspondence has been extended to multiple setting in classical computer, it has yet to emerge in quantum computing. To address those problems we follow two different approaches: the first one, through the development of a linear and reversible programming language, capturing a subset of quantum computing, along with a Curry-Howard correspondence with the logic µMALL. The language comes in two versions: one representing exactly complete, reversible functions while the other one can represent partial functions. Both version comes with an expressivity result: in the former, one can capture the whole class of Primitive Recursive Functions, while in the later any Turing Machine we show how to capture any Turing Machine. The second approach follows the development of token-based semantics, inspired by Girard’s Geometry of Interaction, for graphical language for quantum computation. In this approach, a token-based semantics was given for the ZX-Calculus: a graphical language for quantum computation capable of representing any linear operators. We show how the token-based semantics matches the denotational one. We extend the ZX-Calculus with a coproduct and an explicit tensor in the development of the Many-Worlds Calculus. This new languages comes with a token-based semantics and an equational theory. We show how quantum control can be represented in this system. Finally, the programming language is modified to be able to realize pure quantum computation and the graphical language is then used as a denotational model for it. </description><author>Kostia Chardonnet</author><pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://theses.hal.science/tel-03959403/document</guid></item><item><title>Equivariant quantum graph circuits: constructions for universal approximation over graphs</title><link>https://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s42484-022-00086-w</link><description>We investigate quantum circuits for graph representation learning, and propose equivariant quantum graph circuits (EQGCs), as a class of parameterized quantum circuits with strong relational inductive bias for learning over graph-structured data. Conceptually, EQGCs serve as a unifying framework for quantum graph representation learning, allowing us to define several interesting subclasses subsuming existing proposals. In terms of the representation power, we prove that the subclasses of interest are universal approximators for functions over the bounded graph domain. This theoretical perspective on quantum graph machine learning methods opens many directions for further work, and could lead to models with capabilities beyond those of classical approaches. We also provide experimental evidence, and observe that the performance of EQGCs scales well with the depth of the model.</description><author>Péter Mernyei, Konstantinos Meichanetzidis and İsmail \̇lkan Ceylan</author><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s42484-022-00086-w</guid></item><item><title>Towards a compiler toolchain for quantum programs</title><link>https://lmf.cnrs.fr/downloads/Perso/thesis-aborgna.pdf</link><description>In this thesis, we present various contributions to the different stages of a quantum compiler toolchain. Our first contribution is the definition of a new intermediate representation for quantum programs based on an extension of the ZX calculus called Scalable ZX (SZX), which allows us to compactly represent quantum circuits repeated structure. We introduce a non-trivial fragment of the Proto-Quipper-D language and present its encoding into families of such SZX-diagrams, that can be used to optimize recurrent segments of the program in a single optimization pass. This intermediate representation can then be transformed into a ZX diagram or a quantum circuit to continue the compilation process. This work was first presented at the International Workshop on Programming Languages for Quantum Computing (PLanQC 2022), and a full version was published in the proceedings of the Quantum Physics and Logic Conference (QPL 2022). A second contribution of this work is the definition of a new optimization procedure for quantum circuits containing both quantum and classical segments, based on the method by Duncan et al. We are able to use an extension of the ZX calculus called ZX Ground to represent such hybrid programs, and optimize programs that encode some communication between the quantum and classical components. A preliminary version of this work was first presented in the proceedings of the International Workshop on Quantum Compilation (IWQC 2020), and finally published at the Asian Symposium on Programming Languages and Systems (APLAS 2021). We have implemented our optimization procedure as an extension of the ZX-diagram manipulation tool pyzx, and upstreamed some of the changes to the main repository. Finally, our last contribution pertains to the detection of classical segments in a hybrid quantum-classical circuit. Some automated optimization processes such as the one we present may produce circuits that computes quantumly some operations that could be performed classically using fewer resources. We formalise the classicalisation problem and present an efficient heuristic to detect such segments. This work was developed jointly with the optimization procedure for hybrid quantum-classical circuits, and a succinct version was published along it at APLAS 2021.</description><author>Agustín Borgna</author><pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://lmf.cnrs.fr/downloads/Perso/thesis-aborgna.pdf</guid></item><item><title>Graphical quantum Clifford-encoder compilers from the ZX calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2301.02356</link><description>We present a quantum compilation algorithm that maps Clifford encoders, an equivalence class of quantum circuits that arise universally in quantum error correction, into a representation in the ZX calculus. In particular, we develop a canonical form in the ZX calculus and prove canonicity as well as efficient reducibility of any Clifford encoder into the canonical form. The diagrams produced by our compiler explicitly visualize information propagation and entanglement structure of the encoder, revealing properties that may be obscured in the circuit or stabilizer-tableau representation.</description><author>Andrey Boris Khesin, Jonathan Z. Lu and Peter W. Shor</author><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2301.02356</guid></item><item><title>Classically Simulating Quantum Supremacy IQP Circuits trough a Random Graph Approach</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.08609</link><description>Quantum Supremacy is a demonstration of a computation by a quantum computer that can not be performed by the best classical computer in a reasonable time. A well-studied approach to demonstrating this on near-term quantum computers is to use random circuit sampling. It has been suggested that a good candidate for demonstrating quantum supremacy with random circuit sampling is to use \emphIQP circuits. These are quantum circuits where the unitary it implements is diagonal. In this paper we introduce improved techniques for classically simulating random IQP circuits. We find a simple algorithm to calculate an amplitude of an $n$-qubit IQP circuit with dense random two-qubit interactions in time $O(\fracłog^2 nn 2^n )$, which for sparse circuits (where each qubit interacts with $O(łog n)$ other qubits) runs in $o(2^n/\textpoly(n))$ for any given polynomial. Using a more complicated stabiliser decomposition approach we improve the algorithm for dense circuits to $Ołeft(\frac(łog n)^4-βn^2-β 2^n i̊ght)$ where $β ≈ 0.396$. We benchmarked our algorithm and found that we can simulate up to 50-qubit circuits in a couple of minutes on a laptop. We estimate that 70-qubit circuits are within reach for a large computing cluster.</description><author>Julien Codsi and John van de Wetering</author><pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.08609</guid></item><item><title>A Graphical #SAT Algorithm for Formulae with Small Clause Density</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.08048</link><description>We study the counting version of the Boolean satisfiability problem #SAT using the ZH-calculus, a graphical language originally introduced to reason about quantum circuits. Using this we find a natural extension of #SAT which we call $#SAT_±$, where variables are additionally labeled by phases, which is GapP-complete. Using graphical reasoning, we find a reduction from #SAT to $#2SAT_±$ in the ZH-calculus. We observe that the DPLL algorithm for #2SAT can be adapted to $#2SAT_±$ directly and hence that Wahlstrom's $O^*(1.2377^n)$ upper bound applies to $#2SAT_±$ as well. Combining this with our reduction from #SAT to $#2SAT_±$ gives us novel upper bounds in terms of clauses and variables that are better than $O^*(2^n)$ for small clause densities of $\fracmn &lt; 2.25$. This is to our knowledge the first non-trivial upper bound for #SAT that is independent of clause size. Our algorithm improves on Dubois' upper bound for $#kSAT$ whenever $\fracmn &lt; 1.85$ and $k ≥ 4$, and the Williams' average-case analysis whenever $\fracmn &lt; 1.21$ and $k ≥ 6$. We also obtain an unconditional upper bound of $O^*(1.88^m)$ for $#4SAT$ in terms of clauses only, and find an improved bound on $#3SAT$ for $1.2577 &lt; \fracmn łeq \frac73$. Our results demonstrate that graphical reasoning can lead to new algorithmic insights, even outside the domain of quantum computing that the calculus was intended for.</description><author>Tuomas Laakkonen, Konstantinos Meichanetzidis and John van de Wetering</author><pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.08048</guid></item></channel></rss>