<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2022 09:38:23 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Complete flow-preserving rewrite rules for MBQC patterns with Pauli measurements</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.02009</link><description>In the one-way model of measurement-based quantum computation (MBQC), computation proceeds via measurements on some standard resource state. So-called flow conditions ensure that the overall computation is deterministic in a suitable sense, with Pauli flow being the most general of these. Existing work on rewriting MBQC patterns while preserving the existence of flow has focused on rewrites that reduce the number of qubits.   In this work, we show that introducing new $Z$-measured qubits, connected to any subset of the existing qubits, preserves the existence of Pauli flow. Furthermore, we give a unique canonical form for stabilizer ZX-diagrams inspired by recent work of Hu &amp; Khesin [arXiv:2109.10210]. We prove that any MBQC-like stabilizer ZX-diagram with Pauli flow can be rewritten into this canonical form using only rules which preserve the existence of Pauli flow and that each of these rules can be reversed while also preserving the existence of Pauli flow. Hence we have complete graphical rewriting for MBQC-like stabilizer ZX-diagrams with Pauli flow.</description><author>Tommy McElvanney and Miriam Backens</author><pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2205.02009</guid></item><item><title>Phase-free ZX diagrams are CSS codes (...or how to graphically grok the surface code)</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2204.14038</link><description>In this paper, we demonstrate a direct correspondence between phase-free ZX diagrams, a graphical notation for representing and manipulating a certain class of linear maps on qubits, and Calderbank-Shor-Steane (CSS) codes, a large family of quantum error correcting codes constructed from classical codes, including for example the Steane code, surface codes, and colour codes. The stabilisers of a CSS code have an especially nice structure arising from a pair of orthogonal $\mathbb F_2$-linear subspaces, or in the case of maximal CSS codes, a single subspace and its orthocomplement. On the other hand, phase-free ZX diagrams can always be efficiently reduced to a normal form given by the basis elements of an $\mathbb F_2$-linear subspace. Here, we will show that these two ways of describing a quantum state by an $\mathbb F_2$-linear subspace $S$ are in fact the same. Namely, the maximal CSS code generated by $S$ fixes the quantum state whose ZX normal form is also given by $S$.   This insight gives us an immediate translation from stabilisers of a maximal CSS code into a ZX diagram describing its associated state. We show that we can extend this translation to stabilisers and logical operators of any (possibly non-maximal) CSS code by "bending wires". To demonstrate the utility of this translation, we give a simple picture of the surface code and a fully graphical derivation of the action of physical lattice surgery operations on the space of logical qubits, completing the ZX presentation of lattice surgery initiated by de Beudrap and Horsman.</description><author>Aleks Kissinger</author><pubDate>Fri, 29 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2204.14038</guid></item><item><title>The Many-Worlds Calculus: Representing Quantum Control</title><link>https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-03654190</link><description>We propose a new typed graphical language for quantum computation, based on compact categories with biproducts. Our language generalizes existing approaches such as ZX-calculus and quantum circuits, while offering a natural framework to support quantum control: it natively supports "quantum tests". The language comes equipped with a denotational semantics based on linear applications, and an equational theory. Through the use of normal forms for the diagrams, we prove the language to be universal, and the equational theory to be complete with respect to the semantics.</description><author>Kostia Chardonnet, Marc de Visme, Benoit Valiron and Renaud Vilmart</author><pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-03654190</guid></item><item><title>Phase gadget compilation for diagonal qutrit gates</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2204.13681</link><description>Phase gadgets have proved to be an indispensable tool for reasoning about ZX-diagrams, being used in optimisation and simulation of quantum circuits and the theory of measurement-based quantum computation. In this paper we study phase gadgets for qutrits. We present the flexsymmetric variant of the original qutrit ZX-calculus, which allows for rewriting that is closer in spirit to the original (qubit) ZX-calculus. In this calculus phase gadgets look as you would expect, but there are non-trivial differences in their properties. We devise new qutrit-specific tricks to extend the graphical Fourier theory of qubits, resulting in a translation between the 'additive' phase gadgets and a 'multiplicative' counterpart we dub phase multipliers. This enables us to build different types of qutrit multiple-controlled phase gates. As an application of these results we find a construction for emulating arbitrary qubit diagonal unitaries, and specifically find an emulation for the qubit CCZ gate that only requires three single-qutrit non-Clifford gates to implement - provably lower than the four T gates needed using just qubit gates.</description><author>John van de Wetering and Lia Yeh</author><pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2204.13681</guid></item><item><title>Completeness of Sum-Over-Paths for Toffoli-Hadamard and the Clifford Hierarchy</title><link>https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-03654438</link><description>The "Sum-Over-Paths" formalism is a way to symbolically manipulate linear maps that describe quantum systems, and is a tool that is used in formal verification. We give here a new set of rewrite rules for the formalism, and show that it is complete for "Toffoli-Hadamard", the simplest approximately universal fragment of quantum mechanics. We show that the rewriting is terminating, but not confluent (which is expected from the universality of the fragment). We do so using the connection between Sum-over-Paths and graphical language ZH-Calculus, and also show how the axiomatization translates into the latter. Finally, we show how to enrich the rewrite system to reach completeness for the whole Clifford hierarchy.</description><author>Renaud Vilmart</author><pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-03654438</guid></item><item><title>Quantum Linear Optics via String Diagrams</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2204.12985</link><description>We establish a formal bridge between qubit-based and photonic quantum computing. We do this by defining a functor from the ZX calculus to linear optical circuits. In the process we provide a compositional theory of quantum linear optics which allows to reason about events involving multiple photons such as those required to perform linear-optical and fusion-based quantum computing.</description><author>Giovanni de Felice and Bob Coecke</author><pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2204.12985</guid></item><item><title>Qudit lattice surgery</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2204.13228</link><description>We observe that lattice surgery, a model of fault-tolerant qubit computation, generalises straightforwardly to arbitrary finite-dimensional qudits. The generalised model is based on the group algebras $ℂℤ_d$ for $d ≥ 2$. It still requires magic state injection for universal quantum computation. We relate the model to the ZX-calculus, a diagrammatic language based on Hopf-Frobenius algebras.</description><author>Alexander Cowtan</author><pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2204.13228</guid></item><item><title>Complete ZX-calculi for the stabiliser fragment in odd prime dimensions</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2204.12531</link><description>We introduce a family of ZX-calculi which axiomatise the stabiliser fragment of quantum theory in odd prime dimensions. These calculi recover many of the nice features of the qubit ZX-calculus which were lost in previous proposals for higher-dimensional systems. We then prove that these calculi are complete, i.e. provide a set of rewrite rules which can be used to prove any equality of stabiliser quantum operations. Adding a discard construction, we obtain a calculus complete for mixed state stabiliser quantum mechanics in odd prime dimensions, and this furthermore gives a complete axiomatisation for the related diagrammatic language for affine co-isotropic relations.</description><author>Robert I. Booth and Titouan Carette</author><pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2204.12531</guid></item><item><title>Large-scale quantum diagrammatic reasoning tools, !-boxes vs. scalable notations</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2204.11702</link><description>The application of diagrammatic reasoning techniques to large-scale quantum processes needs specific tools to describe families of diagrams of arbitrary size. For now, large-scale diagrammatic reasoning tools in ZH-calculus come in two flavours, !-boxes and scalable notations. This paper investigates the interactions between the two approaches by exhibiting correspondences through various examples from the literature, focusing on (hyper)graph states and diagrammatic transforms. In doing so, we set up a path toward a neat and tidy large-scale diagrammatic reasoning toolbox.</description><author>Titouan Carette and Louis Lemonnier</author><pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2204.11702</guid></item><item><title>ZX Polynomial Synthesis</title><link>https://mediatum.ub.tum.de/doc/1658567/0cqw8i7hoo3k7g3wsrbs0k51m.pdf</link><description>The Noisy intermediate state quantum devices era (NISQ era) in quantum computing can be seen as the era of quantum devices with 50-100 qubits, which provide restricted connectivity between qubits and nosy qubits with a limited coherence time. This issue motivates efficient algorithms to reduce the number of gates applied to circuits in an automated way, similar to the simplification process of classical compilers. Various researchers have proposed methods that reduce the number of gates, and the depth of the quantum circuit. Nevertheless, providing a routed circuit, so a circuit that suffices the connectivity graph of the device was always considered a process that is done after optimization. Griend et al. has proposed a recursive algorithm for synthesizing so-called Z polynomials. Moreover, they showed that optimization and routing in combination are pretty effective for Z Polynomials. Hence they proposed the avenue of future work to extend their algorithm to Pauli gadgets. This guided research aims to analyze the problem of general phase gadget synthesis. Herefore we provide two extensions to the algorithm by Griend et al.. One extension focuses on splitting the ZX Polynomial into smaller commuting regions, while the other tries to identify blocking columns and resolve them beforehand. Next, we provide an algorithm based on the A* search heuristic. Finally, we compare our results to the Pauli-Gadet simplification-pass by tket combined with their internal routing strategy and our optimization strategy with pyzx concerning one qubit gates</description><author>David Winderl</author><pubDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://mediatum.ub.tum.de/doc/1658567/0cqw8i7hoo3k7g3wsrbs0k51m.pdf</guid></item></channel></rss>