<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2023 18:09:06 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Graphical quantum Clifford-encoder compilers from the ZX calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2301.02356</link><description>We present a quantum compilation algorithm that maps Clifford encoders, an equivalence class of quantum circuits that arise universally in quantum error correction, into a representation in the ZX calculus. In particular, we develop a canonical form in the ZX calculus and prove canonicity as well as efficient reducibility of any Clifford encoder into the canonical form. The diagrams produced by our compiler explicitly visualize information propagation and entanglement structure of the encoder, revealing properties that may be obscured in the circuit or stabilizer-tableau representation.</description><author>Andrey Boris Khesin, Jonathan Z. Lu and Peter W. Shor</author><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2301.02356</guid></item><item><title>Classically Simulating Quantum Supremacy IQP Circuits trough a Random Graph Approach</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.08609</link><description>Quantum Supremacy is a demonstration of a computation by a quantum computer that can not be performed by the best classical computer in a reasonable time. A well-studied approach to demonstrating this on near-term quantum computers is to use random circuit sampling. It has been suggested that a good candidate for demonstrating quantum supremacy with random circuit sampling is to use \emphIQP circuits. These are quantum circuits where the unitary it implements is diagonal. In this paper we introduce improved techniques for classically simulating random IQP circuits. We find a simple algorithm to calculate an amplitude of an $n$-qubit IQP circuit with dense random two-qubit interactions in time $O(\fracłog^2 nn 2^n )$, which for sparse circuits (where each qubit interacts with $O(łog n)$ other qubits) runs in $o(2^n/\textpoly(n))$ for any given polynomial. Using a more complicated stabiliser decomposition approach we improve the algorithm for dense circuits to $Ołeft(\frac(łog n)^4-βn^2-β 2^n i̊ght)$ where $β ≈ 0.396$. We benchmarked our algorithm and found that we can simulate up to 50-qubit circuits in a couple of minutes on a laptop. We estimate that 70-qubit circuits are within reach for a large computing cluster.</description><author>Julien Codsi and John van de Wetering</author><pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.08609</guid></item><item><title>A Graphical #SAT Algorithm for Formulae with Small Clause Density</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.08048</link><description>We study the counting version of the Boolean satisfiability problem #SAT using the ZH-calculus, a graphical language originally introduced to reason about quantum circuits. Using this we find a natural extension of #SAT which we call $#SAT_±$, where variables are additionally labeled by phases, which is GapP-complete. Using graphical reasoning, we find a reduction from #SAT to $#2SAT_±$ in the ZH-calculus. We observe that the DPLL algorithm for #2SAT can be adapted to $#2SAT_±$ directly and hence that Wahlstrom's $O^*(1.2377^n)$ upper bound applies to $#2SAT_±$ as well. Combining this with our reduction from #SAT to $#2SAT_±$ gives us novel upper bounds in terms of clauses and variables that are better than $O^*(2^n)$ for small clause densities of $\fracmn &lt; 2.25$. This is to our knowledge the first non-trivial upper bound for #SAT that is independent of clause size. Our algorithm improves on Dubois' upper bound for $#kSAT$ whenever $\fracmn &lt; 1.85$ and $k ≥ 4$, and the Williams' average-case analysis whenever $\fracmn &lt; 1.21$ and $k ≥ 6$. We also obtain an unconditional upper bound of $O^*(1.88^m)$ for $#4SAT$ in terms of clauses only, and find an improved bound on $#3SAT$ for $1.2577 &lt; \fracmn łeq \frac73$. Our results demonstrate that graphical reasoning can lead to new algorithmic insights, even outside the domain of quantum computing that the calculus was intended for.</description><author>Tuomas Laakkonen, Konstantinos Meichanetzidis and John van de Wetering</author><pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.08048</guid></item><item><title>Category Theory for Quantum Natural Language Processing</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.06615</link><description>This thesis introduces quantum natural language processing (QNLP) models based on a simple yet powerful analogy between computational linguistics and quantum mechanics: grammar as entanglement. The grammatical structure of text and sentences connects the meaning of words in the same way that entanglement structure connects the states of quantum systems. Category theory allows to make this language-to-qubit analogy formal: it is a monoidal functor from grammar to vector spaces. We turn this abstract analogy into a concrete algorithm that translates the grammatical structure onto the architecture of parameterised quantum circuits. We then use a hybrid classical-quantum algorithm to train the model so that evaluating the circuits computes the meaning of sentences in data-driven tasks.   The implementation of QNLP models motivated the development of DisCoPy (Distributional Compositional Python), the toolkit for applied category theory of which the first chapter gives a comprehensive overview. String diagrams are the core data structure of DisCoPy, they allow to reason about computation at a high level of abstraction. We show how they can encode both grammatical structures and quantum circuits, but also logical formulae, neural networks or arbitrary Python code. Monoidal functors allow to translate these abstract diagrams into concrete computation, interfacing with optimised task-specific libraries.   The second chapter uses DisCopy to implement QNLP models as parameterised functors from grammar to quantum circuits. It gives a first proof-of-concept for the more general concept of functorial learning: generalising machine learning from functions to functors by learning from diagram-like data. In order to learn optimal functor parameters via gradient descent, we introduce the notion of diagrammatic differentiation: a graphical calculus for computing the gradients of parameterised diagrams.</description><author>Alexis Toumi</author><pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.06615</guid></item><item><title>How to sum and exponentiate Hamiltonians in ZXW calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.04462</link><description>This paper develops practical summation techniques in ZXW calculus to reason about quantum dynamics, such as unitary time evolution. First we give a direct representation of a wide class of sums of linear operators, including arbitrary qubits Hamiltonians, in ZXW calculus. As an application, we demonstrate the linearity of the Schrödinger equation and give a diagrammatic representation of the Hamiltonian in Greene-Diniz et al (Gabriel, 2022), which is the first paper that models carbon capture using quantum computing. We then use the Cayley-Hamilton theorem to show in principle how to exponentiate arbitrary qubits Hamiltonians in ZXW calculus. Finally, we develop practical techniques and show how to do Taylor expansion and Trotterization diagrammatically for Hamiltonian simulation. This sets up the framework for using ZXW calculus to the problems in quantum chemistry and condensed matter physics.</description><author>Razin A. Shaikh, Quanlong Wang and Richie Yeung</author><pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.04462</guid></item><item><title>Quantum computation on a 19-qubit wide 2d nearest neighbour qubit array</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.01550</link><description>In this paper, we explore the relationship between the width of a qubit lattice constrained in one dimension and physical thresholds for scalable, fault-tolerant quantum computation. To circumvent the traditionally low thresholds of small fixed-width arrays, we deliberately engineer an error bias at the lowest level of encoding using the surface code. We then address this engineered bias at a higher level of encoding using a lattice-surgery surface code bus that exploits this bias, or a repetition code to make logical qubits with unbiased errors out of biased surface code qubits. Arbitrarily low error rates can then be reached by further concatenating with other codes, such as Steane [[7,1,3]] code and the [[15,7,3]] CSS code. This enables a scalable fixed-width quantum computing architecture on a square qubit lattice that is only 19 qubits wide, given physical qubits with an error rate of $8.0\times 10^-4$. This potentially eases engineering issues in systems with fine qubit pitches, such as quantum dots in silicon or gallium arsenide.</description><author>Alexis Shaw, Michael Bremner, Alexandru Paler, Daniel Herr and Simon J. Devitt</author><pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.01550</guid></item><item><title>Active volume: An architecture for efficient fault-tolerant quantum computers with limited non-local connections</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.15465</link><description>In existing general-purpose architectures for surface-code-based fault-tolerant quantum computers, the cost of a quantum computation is determined by the circuit volume, i.e., the number of qubits multiplied by the number of non-Clifford gates. We introduce an architecture using non-2D-local connections in which the cost does not scale with the number of qubits, and instead only with the number of logical operations. Each logical operation has an associated active volume, such that the cost of a quantum computation can be quantified as a sum of active volumes of all operations. For quantum computations with thousands of logical qubits, the active volume can be orders of magnitude lower than the circuit volume. Importantly, the architecture does not require all-to-all connectivity between N logical qubits. Instead, each logical qubit is connected to O(log N) other sites. As an example, we show that, using the same number of logical qubits, a 2048-bit factoring algorithm can be executed 44 times faster than on a general-purpose architecture without non-local connections. With photonic qubits, long-range connections are available and we show how photonic components can be used to construct a fusion-based active-volume quantum computer.</description><author>Daniel Litinski and Naomi Nickerson</author><pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.15465</guid></item><item><title>Qudit ZH-calculus</title><link>https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/roy-thesis.pdf</link><description>The use of quantum graphical calculi, such as the ZX-calculus, has lead to great advances in fields such as quantum circuit optimization. Particularly the ZH-calculus has proven useful for reasoning about higher-level quantum operations, such as Toffoli and Hadamard gates, which form an approximately universal set of gates, for which the qubit ZH-calculus is complete. More recently, quantum computing based on d-ary basis states has gained traction, with the ZX- and ZW-calculi having been generalized to higher dimensions. However, no generalization of the ZH-calculus is known. Such a generalization might lead to new insights about higher-dimensional equivalents of the Toffoli-gate. In this dissertation, we provide this generalization of the qubit ZH-calculus to qudits by generalizing a classification of qubit quantum graphical calculi due to Carette and Jeandel by relaxing a condition that would have excluded a qudit ZH-calculus from being constructed. We then use this generalization to reduce the ruleset of the qubit ZH-calculus by one rule. Additionally, we give a first-of-its-kind algorithm for constructing ZH-diagrams from the matrix representation of linear maps, and use this algorithm to show that, for prime dimension, ZH-calculus is universal.</description><author>Patrick Roy</author><pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/roy-thesis.pdf</guid></item><item><title>Graphical calculus for Tensor Network Contractions</title><link>https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/raj-thesis.pdf</link><description>Quantum computing is an emerging field of research that harnesses the laws of quantum mechanics to solve computationally hard problems. In addition to developing better and bigger quantum computers, a significant challenge is developing techniques to benchmark these devices. Thus, pushing the barrier of classical simulation goes hand in hand with the development of quantum computers. In this dissertation, we hope to leverage the existing work on quantum graphical languages such as the ZX-calculus to aid one of the most prominent classical simulation tools, tensor network methods. By their very nature, graphical languages have a more modular representation of quantum circuits, which could be optimized using the associated rewrite rules of the calculi. We investigate how effective the existing procedures are at enhancing tensor network contractions and propose new strategies based on our observations. Furthermore, we evaluate our strategies using a variety of circuits, including the Sycamore circuits used by Google to demonstrate quantum supremacy in 2019.</description><author>Snehal Raj</author><pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/raj-thesis.pdf</guid></item><item><title>Topological Quantum Computation Through the Lens of Categorical Quantum Mechanics</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.03855</link><description>Unitary fusion categories formalise the algebraic theory of topological quantum computation. We rectify confusion around a category describing an anyonic theory and a category describing topological quantum computation. We show that the latter is a subcategory of Hilb. We represent elements of the Fibonacci and Ising models, namely the encoding of qubits and the associated braid group representations, with the ZX-calculus and show that in both cases, the Yang-Baxter equation is directly connected to an instance of the P-rule of the ZX-calculus. In the Ising case, this reduces to a familiar rule relating two distinct Euler decompositions of the Hadamard gate as $π/2$ phase rotations, whereas in the Fibonacci case, we give a previously unconsidered exact solution of the P-rule involving the Golden ratio. We demonstrate the utility of these representations by giving graphical derivations of the single-qubit braid equations for Fibonacci anyons and the single- and two-qubit braid equations for Ising anyons.</description><author>Fatimah Rita Ahmadi and Aleks Kissinger</author><pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.03855</guid></item></channel></rss>