<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 14:32:16 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Foundations for Near-Term Quantum Natural Language Processing</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.03755</link><description>We provide conceptual and mathematical foundations for near-term quantum natural language processing (QNLP), and do so in quantum computer scientist friendly terms. We opted for an expository presentation style, and provide references for supporting empirical evidence and formal statements concerning mathematical generality.   We recall how the quantum model for natural language that we employ canonically combines linguistic meanings with rich linguistic structure, most notably grammar. In particular, the fact that it takes a quantum-like model to combine meaning and structure, establishes QNLP as quantum-native, on par with simulation of quantum systems. Moreover, the now leading Noisy Intermediate-Scale Quantum (NISQ) paradigm for encoding classical data on quantum hardware, variational quantum circuits, makes NISQ exceptionally QNLP-friendly: linguistic structure can be encoded as a free lunch, in contrast to the apparently exponentially expensive classical encoding of grammar.   Quantum speed-up for QNLP tasks has already been established in previous work with Will Zeng. Here we provide a broader range of tasks which all enjoy the same advantage.   Diagrammatic reasoning is at the heart of QNLP. Firstly, the quantum model interprets language as quantum processes via the diagrammatic formalism of categorical quantum mechanics. Secondly, these diagrams are via ZX-calculus translated into quantum circuits. Parameterisations of meanings then become the circuit variables to be learned.   Our encoding of linguistic structure within quantum circuits also embodies a novel approach for establishing word-meanings that goes beyond the current standards in mainstream AI, by placing linguistic structure at the heart of Wittgenstein's meaning-is-context.</description><author>Bob Coecke, Giovanni de Felice, Konstantinos Meichanetzidis and Alexis Toumi</author><pubDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.03755</guid></item><item><title>AKLT-states as ZX-diagrams: diagrammatic reasoning for quantum states</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.01219</link><description>From Feynman diagrams to tensor networks, diagrammatic representations of computations in quantum mechanics have catalysed progress in physics. These diagrams represent the underlying mathematical operations and aid physical interpretation, but cannot generally be computed with directly. In this paper we introduce the ZXH-calculus, a graphical language based on the ZX-calculus, that we use to represent and reason about many-body states entirely graphically. As a demonstration, we express the 1D AKLT state, a symmetry protected topological state, in the ZXH-calculus by developing a representation of spins higher than 1/2 within the calculus. By exploiting the simplifying power of the ZXH-calculus rules we show how this representation straightforwardly recovers two important properties, the existence of topologically protected edge states, and the non-vanishing of a string order parameter. We furthermore show how the AKLT matrix-product state representation can be recovered from our diagrams. In addition, we provide an alternative proof that the 2D AKLT state on a hexagonal lattice can be reduced to a graph state, demonstrating that it is a universal quantum computing resource. Our results show that the ZXH-calculus is a powerful language for representing and computing with physical states entirely graphically, paving the way to develop more efficient many-body algorithms.</description><author>Richard D. P. East, John van de Wetering, Nicholas Chancellor and Adolfo G. Grushin</author><pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.01219</guid></item><item><title>Graphical calculi and their conjecture synthesis</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.03914</link><description>Categorical Quantum Mechanics, and graphical calculi in particular, has proven to be an intuitive and powerful way to reason about quantum computing. This work continues the exploration of graphical calculi, inside and outside of the quantum computing setting, by investigating the algebraic structures with which we label diagrams. The initial aim for this was Conjecture Synthesis; the algorithmic process of creating theorems. To this process we introduce a generalisation step, which itself requires the ability to infer and then verify parameterised families of theorems. This thesis introduces such inference and verification frameworks, in doing so forging novel links between graphical calculi and fields such as Algebraic Geometry and Galois Theory. These frameworks inspired further research into the design of graphical calculi, and we introduce two important new calculi here. First is the calculus RING, which is initial among ring-based qubit graphical calculi, and in turn inspired the introduction and classification of phase homomorphism pairs also presented here. The second is the calculus ZQ, an edge-decorated calculus which naturally expresses arbitrary qubit rotations, eliminating the need for non-linear rules such as (EU) of ZX. It is expected that these results will be of use to those creating optimisation schemes and intermediate representations for quantum computing, to those creating new graphical calculi, and for those performing conjecture synthesis.</description><author>Hector Miller-Bakewell</author><pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.03914</guid></item><item><title>A Recipe for Quantum Graphical Languages</title><link>https://dx.doi.org/10.4230/LIPIcs.ICALP.2020.118</link><description>Different graphical calculi have been proposed to represent quantum computation. First the ZX- calculus [4], followed by the ZW-calculus [12] and then the ZH-calculus [1]. We can wonder if new Z*-calculi will continue to be proposed forever. This article answers negatively. All those language share a common core structure we call Z*-algebras. We classify Z*-algebras up to isomorphism in two dimensional Hilbert spaces and show that they are all variations of the aforementioned calculi. We do the same for linear relations and show that the calculus of [2] is essentially the unique one.</description><author>Titouan Carette and Emmanuel Jeandel</author><pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2008.04193</guid></item><item><title>A Compositional Model of Consciousness based on Consciousness-Only</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.16138</link><description>Scientific studies of consciousness rely on objects whose existence is independent of any consciousness. This theoretical-assumption leads to the "hard problem" of consciousness. We avoid this problem by assuming consciousness to be fundamental, and the main feature of consciousness is characterized as being other-dependent. We set up a framework which naturally subsumes the other-dependent feature by defining a compact closed category where morphisms represent conscious processes. These morphisms are a composition of a set of generators, each being specified by their relations with other generators, and therefore other-dependent. The framework is general enough, i.e. parameters in the morphisms take values in arbitrary commutative semi-rings, from which any finitely dimensional system can be dealt with. Our proposal fits well into a compositional model of consciousness and is an important step forward that addresses both the hard problem of consciousness and the combination problem of (proto)-panpsychism.</description><author>Camilo Miguel Signorelli, Quanlong Wang and Ilyas Khan</author><pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.16138</guid></item><item><title>Algebraic complete axiomatisation of ZX-calculus with a normal form via elementary matrix operations</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.13739</link><description>In this paper we give a complete axiomatisation of qubit ZX-calculus via elementary transformations which are basic operations in linear algebra. This formalism has two main advantages. First, all the operations of the phases are algebraic ones without trigonometry functions involved, thus paved the way for generalising complete axiomatisation of qubit ZX-calculus to qudit ZX-calculus and ZX-calculus over commutative semirings. Second, we characterise elementary transformations in terms of ZX diagrams, so a lot of linear algebra stuff can be done purely diagrammatically.</description><author>Quanlong Wang</author><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.13739</guid></item><item><title>A Generic Compilation Strategy for the Unitary Coupled Cluster Ansatz</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.10515</link><description>We describe a compilation strategy for Variational Quantum Eigensolver (VQE) algorithms which use the Unitary Coupled Cluster (UCC) ansatz, designed to reduce circuit depth and gate count. This is achieved by partitioning Pauli exponential terms into mutually commuting sets. These sets are then diagonalised using Clifford circuits and synthesised using the phase polynomial formalism. This strategy reduces cx depth by 75.4% on average, and by up to 89.9%, compared to naive synthesis for a variety of molecules, qubit encodings and basis sets.</description><author>Alexander Cowtan, Will Simmons and Ross Duncan</author><pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.10515</guid></item><item><title>Parts of Speech Tagging in NLP: Runtime Optimization with Quantum Formulation and ZX Calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.10328</link><description>This paper proposes an optimized formulation of the parts of speech tagging in Natural Language Processing with a quantum computing approach and further demonstrates the quantum gate-level runnable optimization with ZX-calculus, keeping the implementation target in the context of Noisy Intermediate Scale Quantum Systems (NISQ). Our quantum formulation exhibits quadratic speed up over the classical counterpart and further demonstrates the implementable optimization with the help of ZX calculus postulates.</description><author>Arit Kumar Bishwas, Ashish Mani and Vasile Palade</author><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jul 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.10328</guid></item><item><title>Colored props for large scale graphical reasoning</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.03564</link><description>The prop formalism allows representation of processes withstring diagrams and has been successfully applied in various areas such as quantum computing, electric circuits and control flow graphs. However, these graphical approaches suffer from scalability problems when it comes to writing large diagrams. A proposal to tackle this issue has been investigated for ZX-calculus using colored props. This paper extends the approach to any prop, making it a general tool for graphical languages manipulation.</description><author>Titouan Carette and Simon Perdrix</author><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2007.03564</guid></item><item><title>Well-tempered ZX and ZH calculi</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.02557</link><description>The ZX calculus is a mathematical tool to represent and analyse quantum operations by manipulating diagrams which in effect represent tensor networks. Two families of nodes of these networks are ones which commute with either Z rotations or X rotations, usually called "green nodes" and "red nodes" respectively. The original formulation of the ZX calculus was motivated in part by properties of the algebras formed by the green and red nodes: notably, that they form a bialgebra -- but only up to scalar factors. As a consequence, the diagram transformations and notation for certain unitary operations involve "scalar gadgets" which denote contributions to a normalising factor. We present renormalised generators for the ZX calculus, which form a bialgebra precisely. As a result, no scalar gadgets are required to represent the most common unitary transformations, and the corresponding diagram transformations are generally simpler. We also present a similar renormalised version of the ZH calculus. We obtain these results by an analysis of conditions under which various "idealised" rewrites are sound, leveraging the existing presentations of the ZX and ZH calculi.</description><author>Niel de Beaudrap</author><pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.02557</guid></item></channel></rss>