<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Apr 2022 16:20:52 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>The Many-Worlds Calculus: Representing Quantum Control</title><link>https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-03654190</link><description>We propose a new typed graphical language for quantum computation, based on compact categories with biproducts. Our language generalizes existing approaches such as ZX-calculus and quantum circuits, while offering a natural framework to support quantum control: it natively supports "quantum tests". The language comes equipped with a denotational semantics based on linear applications, and an equational theory. Through the use of normal forms for the diagrams, we prove the language to be universal, and the equational theory to be complete with respect to the semantics.</description><author>Kostia Chardonnet, Marc de Visme, Benoit Valiron and Renaud Vilmart</author><pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-03654190</guid></item><item><title>Phase gadget compilation for diagonal qutrit gates</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2204.13681</link><description>Phase gadgets have proved to be an indispensable tool for reasoning about ZX-diagrams, being used in optimisation and simulation of quantum circuits and the theory of measurement-based quantum computation. In this paper we study phase gadgets for qutrits. We present the flexsymmetric variant of the original qutrit ZX-calculus, which allows for rewriting that is closer in spirit to the original (qubit) ZX-calculus. In this calculus phase gadgets look as you would expect, but there are non-trivial differences in their properties. We devise new qutrit-specific tricks to extend the graphical Fourier theory of qubits, resulting in a translation between the 'additive' phase gadgets and a 'multiplicative' counterpart we dub phase multipliers. This enables us to build different types of qutrit multiple-controlled phase gates. As an application of these results we find a construction for emulating arbitrary qubit diagonal unitaries, and specifically find an emulation for the qubit CCZ gate that only requires three single-qutrit non-Clifford gates to implement - provably lower than the four T gates needed using just qubit gates.</description><author>John van de Wetering and Lia Yeh</author><pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2204.13681</guid></item><item><title>Quantum Linear Optics via String Diagrams</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2204.12985</link><description>We establish a formal bridge between qubit-based and photonic quantum computing. We do this by defining a functor from the ZX calculus to linear optical circuits. In the process we provide a compositional theory of quantum linear optics which allows to reason about events involving multiple photons such as those required to perform linear-optical and fusion-based quantum computing.</description><author>Giovanni de Felice and Bob Coecke</author><pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2204.12985</guid></item><item><title>Qudit lattice surgery</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2204.13228</link><description>We observe that lattice surgery, a model of fault-tolerant qubit computation, generalises straightforwardly to arbitrary finite-dimensional qudits. The generalised model is based on the group algebras $ℂℤ_d$ for $d ≥ 2$. It still requires magic state injection for universal quantum computation. We relate the model to the ZX-calculus, a diagrammatic language based on Hopf-Frobenius algebras.</description><author>Alexander Cowtan</author><pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2204.13228</guid></item><item><title>Complete ZX-calculi for the stabiliser fragment in odd prime dimensions</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2204.12531</link><description>We introduce a family of ZX-calculi which axiomatise the stabiliser fragment of quantum theory in odd prime dimensions. These calculi recover many of the nice features of the qubit ZX-calculus which were lost in previous proposals for higher-dimensional systems. We then prove that these calculi are complete, i.e. provide a set of rewrite rules which can be used to prove any equality of stabiliser quantum operations. Adding a discard construction, we obtain a calculus complete for mixed state stabiliser quantum mechanics in odd prime dimensions, and this furthermore gives a complete axiomatisation for the related diagrammatic language for affine co-isotropic relations.</description><author>Robert I. Booth and Titouan Carette</author><pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2204.12531</guid></item><item><title>Diagrammatic Analysis for Parameterized Quantum Circuits</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2204.01307</link><description>Diagrammatic representations of quantum algorithms and circuits offer novel approaches to their design and analysis. In this work, we describe extensions of the ZX-calculus especially suitable for parameterized quantum circuits, in particular for computing observable expectation values as functions of or for fixed parameters, which are important algorithmic quantities in a variety of applications ranging from combinatorial optimization to quantum chemistry. We provide several new ZX-diagram rewrite rules and generalizations for this setting. In particular, we give formal rules for dealing with linear combinations of ZX-diagrams, where the relative complex-valued scale factors of each diagram must be kept track of, in contrast to most previously studied single-diagram realizations where these coefficients can be effectively ignored. This allows us to directly import a number useful relations from the operator analysis to ZX-calculus setting, including causal cone and quantum gate commutation rules. We demonstrate that the diagrammatic approach offers useful insights into algorithm structure and performance by considering several ansätze from the literature including realizations of hardware-efficient ans\ẗze and QAOA. We find that by employing a diagrammatic representation, calculations across different ans\"z̈e can become more intuitive and potentially easier approach systematically than by alternative means. Finally, we outline how diagrammatic approaches may aid in the design and study of new and more effective quantum circuit ans\"aë.</description><author>Tobias Stollenwerk and Stuart Hadfield</author><pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2204.01307</guid></item><item><title>Addition and Differentiation of ZX-diagrams</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2202.11386</link><description>The ZX-calculus is a powerful framework for reasoning in quantum computing. It provides in particular a compact representation of matrices of interests. A peculiar property of the ZX-calculus is the absence of a formal sum allowing the linear combinations of arbitrary ZX-diagrams. The universality of the formalism guarantees however that for any two ZX-diagrams, the sum of their interpretations can be represented by a ZX-diagram. We introduce a general, inductive definition of the addition of ZX-diagrams, relying on the construction of controlled diagrams. Based on this addition technique, we provide an inductive differentiation of ZX-diagrams.   Indeed, given a ZX-diagram with variables in the description of its angles, one can differentiate the diagram according to one of these variables. Differentiation is ubiquitous in quantum mechanics and quantum computing (e.g. for solving optimization problems). Technically, differentiation of ZX-diagrams is strongly related to summation as witnessed by the product rules.   We also introduce an alternative, non inductive, differentiation technique rather based on the isolation of the variables. Finally, we apply our results to deduce a diagram for an Ising Hamiltonian.</description><author>Emmanuel Jeandel, Simon Perdrix and Margarita Veshchezerova</author><pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2202.11386</guid></item><item><title>Classical simulation of quantum circuits with partial and graphical stabiliser decompositions</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2202.09202</link><description>Recent developments in classical simulation of quantum circuits make use of clever decompositions of chunks of magic states into sums of efficiently simulable stabiliser states. We show here how, by considering certain non-stabiliser entangled states which have more favourable decompositions, we can speed up these simulations. This is made possible by using the ZX-calculus, which allows us to easily find instances of these entangled states in the simplified diagram representing the quantum circuit to be simulated. We additionally find a new technique of partial stabiliser decompositions that allow us to trade magic states for stabiliser terms. With this technique we require only $2^α t$ stabiliser terms, where $α≈ 0.396$, to simulate a circuit with T-count $t$. This matches the $α$ found by Qassim et al., but whereas they only get this scaling in the asymptotic limit, ours applies for a circuit of any size. Our method builds upon a recently proposed scheme for simulation combining stabiliser decompositions and optimisation strategies implemented in the software QuiZX. With our techniques we manage to reliably simulate 50-qubit 1400 T-count hidden shift circuits in a couple of minutes on a consumer laptop.</description><author>Aleks Kissinger, John van de Wetering and Renaud Vilmart</author><pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2202.09202</guid></item><item><title>Circuit Extraction for ZX-diagrams can be #P-hard</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2202.09194</link><description>The ZX-calculus is a graphical language for reasoning about quantum computation using ZX-diagrams, a certain flexible generalisation of quantum circuits that can be used to represent linear maps from $m$ to $n$ qubits for any $m,n ≥ 0$. Some applications for the ZX-calculus, such as quantum circuit optimisation and synthesis, rely on being able to efficiently translate a ZX-diagram back into a quantum circuit of comparable size. While several sufficient conditions are known for describing families of ZX-diagrams that can be efficiently transformed back into circuits, it has previously been conjectured that the general problem of circuit extraction is hard. That is, that it should not be possible to efficiently convert an arbitrary ZX-diagram describing a unitary linear map into an equivalent quantum circuit. In this paper we prove this conjecture by showing that the circuit extraction problem is #P-hard, and so is itself at least as hard as strong simulation of quantum circuits. In addition to our main hardness result, which relies specifically on the circuit representation, we give a representation-agnostic hardness result. Namely, we show that any oracle that takes as input a ZX-diagram description of a unitary and produces samples of the output of the associated quantum computation enables efficient probabilistic solutions to NP-complete problems.</description><author>Niel de Beaudrap, Aleks Kissinger and John van de Wetering</author><pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2202.09194</guid></item><item><title>Differentiating and Integrating ZX Diagrams</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.13250</link><description>ZX-calculus has proved to be a useful tool for quantum technology with a wide range of successful applications. Most of these applications are of an algebraic nature. However, other tasks that involve differentiation and integration remain unreachable with current ZX techniques. Here we elevate ZX to an analytical perspective by realising differentiation and integration entirely within the framework of ZX-calculus. We explicitly illustrate the new analytic framework of ZX-calculus by applying it in context of quantum machine learning.</description><author>Quanlong Wang and Richie Yeung</author><pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.13250</guid></item></channel></rss>