<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2023 17:22:14 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Unifying flavors of fault tolerance with the ZX calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08829</link><description>There are several models of quantum computation which exhibit shared fundamental fault-tolerance properties. This article makes commonalities explicit by presenting these different models in a unifying framework based on the ZX calculus. We focus on models of topological fault tolerance - specifically surface codes - including circuit-based, measurement-based and fusion-based quantum computation, as well as the recently introduced model of Floquet codes. We find that all of these models can be viewed as different flavors of the same underlying stabilizer fault-tolerance structure, and sustain this through a set of local equivalence transformations which allow mapping between flavors. We anticipate that this unifying perspective will pave the way to transferring progress among the different views of stabilizer fault-tolerance and help researchers familiar with one model easily understand others.</description><author>Hector Bombin, Daniel Litinski, Naomi Nickerson, Fernando Pastawski and Sam Roberts</author><pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08829</guid></item><item><title>Modular decoding: parallelizable real-time decoding for quantum computers</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.04846</link><description>Universal fault-tolerant quantum computation will require real-time decoding algorithms capable of quickly extracting logical outcomes from the stream of data generated by noisy quantum hardware. We propose modular decoding, an approach capable of addressing this challenge with minimal additional communication and without sacrificing decoding accuracy. We introduce the edge-vertex decomposition, a concrete instance of modular decoding for lattice-surgery style fault-tolerant blocks which is remarkably effective. This decomposition of the global decoding problem into sub-tasks mirrors the logical-block-network structure of a fault-tolerant quantum circuit. We identify the buffering condition as a key requirement controlling decoder quality; it demands a sufficiently large separation (buffer) between a correction committed by a decoding sub-task and the data unavailable to it. We prove that the fault distance of the protocol is preserved if the buffering condition is satisfied. Finally, we implement edge-vertex modular decoding and apply it on a variety of quantum circuits, including the Clifford component of the 15-to-1 magic-state distillation protocol. Monte Carlo simulations on a range of buffer sizes provide quantitative evidence that buffers are both necessary and sufficient to guarantee decoder accuracy. Our results show that modular decoding meets all the practical requirements necessary to support real-world fault-tolerant quantum computers.</description><author>Héctor Bombín, Chris Dawson, Ye-Hua Liu, Naomi Nickerson, Fernando Pastawski and Sam Roberts</author><pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.04846</guid></item><item><title>Simple Complete Equational Theories for Quantum Circuits with Ancillae or Partial Trace</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.03117</link><description>Although quantum circuits have been ubiquitous for decades in quantum computing, the first complete equational theory for quantum circuits has only recently been introduced. Completeness guarantees that any true equation on quantum circuits can be derived from the equational theory. Our contribution is twofold: (i) We simplify this equational theory by proving that several rules can be derived from the remaining ones. In particular, two out of the three most intricate rules are removed, the third one being slightly simplified. (ii) We extend the complete equational theory to quantum circuits with ancillae or qubit discarding, to represent respectively quantum computations using an additional workspace, and hybrid quantum computations. We show that the remaining intricate rule can be greatly simplified in these more expressive settings. The development of simple and complete equational theories for expressive quantum circuit models opens new avenues for reasoning about quantum circuits. It provides strong formal foundations for various compiling tasks such as circuit optimisation, hardware constraint satisfaction and verification.</description><author>Alexandre Clément, Noé Delorme, Simon Perdrix and Renaud Vilmart</author><pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.03117</guid></item><item><title>Basic ZX-calculus for students and professionals</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.03163</link><description>These are the lecture notes of guest lectures for Artur Ekert's course Introduction to Quantum Information at the Mathematical Institute of Oxford University, Hilary Term 2023. Some basic familiarity with Dirac notation is assumed. For the readers of Quantum in Pictures (QiP) who have some basic quantum background, these notes also constitute the shortest path to an explanation of how what they learn in QIP relates to the traditional quantum formalism.</description><author>Bob Coecke</author><pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.03163</guid></item><item><title>Resource efficient method for representation and measurement of constrained electronic structure states with a quantum computer</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.01122</link><description>We present a novel method for improving the quantum simulation of the ground state energy of molecules. We perform a pre-processing step classically, which reduces the dimensionality of the problem by generating a custom mapping which excludes states which violate problem constraints. Subsequently, a specialized measurement scheme is used to extract the expectation value of the problem Hamiltonian through this mapping. We demonstrate that this method reduces the amount of quantum resources needed to run a Variational Quantum Eigensolver (VQE) algorithm without making any approximations to the physics of the quantum chemistry problem.</description><author>Kaur Kristjuhan and Mark Nicholas Jones</author><pubDate>Thu, 02 Mar 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.01122</guid></item><item><title>Oblivious Transfer from Zero-Knowledge Proofs, or How to Achieve Round-Optimal Quantum Oblivious Transfer and Zero-Knowledge Proofs on Quantum States</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.01476</link><description>We provide a generic construction to turn any classical Zero-Knowledge (ZK) protocol into a composable (quantum) oblivious transfer (OT) protocol, mostly lifting the round-complexity properties and security guarantees (plain-model/statistical security/unstructured functions...) of the ZK protocol to the resulting OT protocol. Such a construction is unlikely to exist classically as Cryptomania is believed to be different from Minicrypt.   In particular, by instantiating our construction using Non-Interactive ZK (NIZK), we provide the first round-optimal (2-message) quantum OT protocol secure in the random oracle model, and round-optimal extensions to string and k-out-of-n OT.   At the heart of our construction lies a new method that allows us to prove properties on a received quantum state without revealing (too much) information on it, even in a non-interactive way and/or with statistical guarantees when using an appropriate classical ZK protocol. We can notably prove that a state has been partially measured (with arbitrary constraints on the set of measured qubits), without revealing any additional information on this set. This notion can be seen as an analog of ZK to quantum states, and we expect it to be of independent interest as it extends complexity theory to quantum languages, as illustrated by the two new complexity classes we introduce, ZKstateQIP and ZKstateQMA.</description><author>Léo Colisson, Garazi Muguruza and Florian Speelman</author><pubDate>Thu, 02 Mar 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2303.01476</guid></item><item><title>Completeness for arbitrary finite dimensions of ZXW-calculus, a unifying calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.12135</link><description>The ZX-calculus is a universal graphical language for qubit quantum computation, meaning that every linear map between qubits can be expressed in the ZX-calculus. Furthermore, it is a complete graphical rewrite system: any equation involving linear maps that is derivable in the Hilbert space formalism for quantum theory can also be derived in the calculus by rewriting. It has widespread usage within quantum industry and academia for a variety of tasks such as quantum circuit optimisation, error-correction, and education.   The ZW-calculus is an alternative universal graphical language that is also complete for qubit quantum computing. In fact, its completeness was used to prove that the ZX-calculus is universally complete. This calculus has advanced how quantum circuits are compiled into photonic hardware architectures in the industry.   Recently, by combining these two calculi, a new calculus has emerged for qubit quantum computation, the ZXW-calculus. Using this calculus, graphical-differentiation, -integration, and -exponentiation were made possible, thus enabling the development of novel techniques in the domains of quantum machine learning and quantum chemistry.   Here, we generalise the ZXW-calculus to arbitrary finite dimensions, that is, to qudits. Moreover, we prove that this graphical rewrite system is complete for any finite dimension. This is the first completeness result for any universal graphical language beyond qubits.</description><author>Boldizsár Poór, Quanlong Wang, Razin Shaikh A., Lia Yeh, Richie Yeung and Bob Coecke</author><pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.12135</guid></item><item><title>Compositionality of planar perfect matchings</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.08767</link><description>We exhibit a strong connection between the matchgate formalism introduced by Valiant and the ZW-calculus of Coecke and Kissinger. This connection provides a natural compositional framework for matchgate theory as well as a direct combinatorial interpretation of the diagrams of ZW-calculus through the perfect matchings of their underlying graphs.   We identify a precise fragment of ZW-calculus, the planar W-calculus, that we prove to be complete and universal for matchgates, that are linear maps satisfying the matchgate identities. Computing scalars of the planar W-calculus corresponds to counting perfect matchings of planar graphs, and so can be carried in polynomial time using the FKT algorithm, making the planar W-calculus an efficiently simulable fragment of the ZW-calculus, in a similar way that the Clifford fragment is for ZX-calculus. This work opens new directions for the investigation of the combinatorial properties of ZW-calculus as well as the study of perfect matching counting through compositional diagrammatical technics.</description><author>Titouan Carette, Etienne Moutot, Thomas Perez and Renaud Vilmart</author><pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.08767</guid></item><item><title>Complete Graphical Language for Hermiticity-Preserving Superoperators</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.04212</link><description>Universal and complete graphical languages have been successfully designed for pure state quantum mechanics, corresponding to linear maps between Hilbert spaces, and mixed states quantum mechanics, corresponding to completely positive superoperators. In this paper, we go one step further and present a universal and complete graphical language for Hermiticity-preserving superoperators. Such a language opens the possibility of diagrammatic compositional investigations of antilinear transformations featured in various physical situations, such as the Choi-Jamiołkowski isomorphism, spin-flip, or entanglement witnesses. Our construction relies on an extension of the ZW-calculus exhibiting a normal form for Hermitian matrices.</description><author>Titouan Carette, Timothée Hoffreumon, Emile Larroque and Renaud Vilmart</author><pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.04212</guid></item><item><title>Cutting multi-control quantum gates with ZX calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.00387</link><description>Circuit cutting, the decomposition of a quantum circuit into independent partitions, has become a promising avenue towards experiments with larger quantum circuits in the noisy-intermediate scale quantum (NISQ) era. While previous work focused on cutting qubit wires or two-qubit gates, in this work we introduce a method for cutting multi-controlled Z gates. We construct a decomposition and prove the upper bound $\mathcalO(6^2K)$ on the associated sampling overhead, where $K$ is the number of cuts in the circuit. This bound is independent of the number of control qubits but can be further reduced to $\mathcalO(4.5^2K)$ for the special case of CCZ gates. Furthermore, we evaluate our proposal on IBM hardware and experimentally show noise resilience due to the strong reduction of CNOT gates in the cut circuits.</description><author>Christian Ufrecht, Maniraman Periyasamy, Sebastian Rietsch, Daniel D. Scherer, Axel Plinge and Christopher Mutschler</author><pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2302.00387</guid></item></channel></rss>