<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Nov 2022 21:57:04 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Graphical calculus for Tensor Network Contractions</title><link>https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/raj-thesis.pdf</link><description>Quantum computing is an emerging field of research that harnesses the laws of quantum mechanics to solve computationally hard problems. In addition to developing better and bigger quantum computers, a significant challenge is developing techniques to benchmark these devices. Thus, pushing the barrier of classical simulation goes hand in hand with the development of quantum computers. In this dissertation, we hope to leverage the existing work on quantum graphical languages such as the ZX-calculus to aid one of the most prominent classical simulation tools, tensor network methods. By their very nature, graphical languages have a more modular representation of quantum circuits, which could be optimized using the associated rewrite rules of the calculi. We investigate how effective the existing procedures are at enhancing tensor network contractions and propose new strategies based on our observations. Furthermore, we evaluate our strategies using a variety of circuits, including the Sycamore circuits used by Google to demonstrate quantum supremacy in 2019.</description><author>Snehal Raj</author><pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/raj-thesis.pdf</guid></item><item><title>On the Verge to Improve Technique of T-count Reduction via Spider Nest Identities</title><link>https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/domitrz-thesis.pdf</link><description>Approximate, universal quantum computation is most commonly described by circuits consisting of Clifford+T gates. The T gate, except being crucial for the universality, is the one which is, in real-world implementations, the most resource-intensive, and the least fault-tolerant of all operations. Because of that, a natural question emerges – how to reduce the number of T gates (or T-count) in a given circuit. The known methods used to reduce the T-count to an optimal value have an exponential running time [24, 2], which motivates the search for an efficient heuristic algorithm. The importance of this problem, along with proposed solutions were discussed in multiple publications including [6, 18, 16, 15, 7, 23]. Spider nest identities, introduced in [16], together with the decomposition of the circuit inspired by [18], were combined in [15] to provide an effective algorithm for T-count reduction. This approach was tested and compared with previous results, and, in some cases, it resulted in a significant improvement of the state of the art. Another advantage of this algorithm was, in contrast to the other results, a significant improvement of the execution time. In this dissertation, we discuss several modifications of the algorithm in order to gain partial outperformance without a significant increase of the running time, which include analysis of the influence of the order of applying the identities, efficient usage of identities generated from small and big spider nests, combining the results obtained in [25] with spider nest identities, and others. Some of these modifications improve or achieve the current state of the art for various circuits. We also provide a quantitative comparison of results, verified using [3] – a tool created alongside [4], on numerous benchmark circuits obtained from [9, 26, 3]. Moreover, we present abstract formulations of considered problem, pose a question of completeness of spider nest identities with respect to T-count reduction, and present different, possibly more elegant, way of phrasing the spider nest identities, as dense spider nest identities.</description><author>Witalis Domitrz</author><pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/domitrz-thesis.pdf</guid></item><item><title>Topological Quantum Computation Through the Lens of Categorical Quantum Mechanics</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.03855</link><description>Unitary fusion categories formalise the algebraic theory of topological quantum computation. We rectify confusion around a category describing an anyonic theory and a category describing topological quantum computation. We show that the latter is a subcategory of Hilb. We represent elements of the Fibonacci and Ising models, namely the encoding of qubits and the associated braid group representations, with the ZX-calculus and show that in both cases, the Yang-Baxter equation is directly connected to an instance of the P-rule of the ZX-calculus. In the Ising case, this reduces to a familiar rule relating two distinct Euler decompositions of the Hadamard gate as $π/2$ phase rotations, whereas in the Fibonacci case, we give a previously unconsidered exact solution of the P-rule involving the Golden ratio. We demonstrate the utility of these representations by giving graphical derivations of the single-qubit braid equations for Fibonacci anyons and the single- and two-qubit braid equations for Ising anyons.</description><author>Fatimah Rita Ahmadi and Aleks Kissinger</author><pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.03855</guid></item><item><title>Cutting-Edge Graphical Stabiliser Decompositions for Classical Simulation of Quantum Circuits</title><link>https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/codsi-thesis.pdf</link><description>The aim of this thesis is to study and improve classical simulation of quan tum circuits with stabiliser decompositions by using the ZX-calculus. We propose more efficient decompositions for a large family of states in addi- tion to integrating graphs cuts to make use of potential low connectivity of ZX-diagrams. We also discovered different heuristics to speed up the simulations. Finally, we implemented our method and compared it with the state-of-the-art on different families of circuits to asses the improvements achieved by our approach.</description><author>Julien Codsi</author><pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/codsi-thesis.pdf</guid></item><item><title>Quantum Machine Learning using the ZXW-Calculus</title><link>https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/koch-thesis.pdf</link><description>The field of quantum machine learning (QML) explores how quantum computers can be used to more efficiently solve machine learning problems. As an application of hybrid quantum-classical algorithms, it promises a potential quantum advantages in the near term. In this thesis, we use the ZXW-calculus to diagrammatically analyse two key problems that QML applications face. First, we discuss algorithms to compute gradients on quantum hardware that are needed to perform gradient-based optimisation for QML. Concretely, we give new diagrammatic proofs of the common 2- and 4-term parameter shift rules used in the literature. Additionally, we derive a novel, generalised parameter shift rule with 2n terms that is applicable to gates that can be represented with n parametrised spiders in the ZXW-calculus. Furthermore, to the best of our knowledge, we give the first proof of a conjecture by Anselmetti et al. by proving a no-go theorem ruling out more efficient alternatives to the 4-term shift rule. Secondly, we analyse the gradient landscape of quantum ans¨atze for barren plateaus using both empirical and analytical techniques. Concretely, we develop a tool that automatically calculates the variance of gradients and use it to detect likely barren plateaus in commonly used quantum ans¨atze. Furthermore, we formally prove the existence or absence of barren plateaus for a selection of ansätze using diagrammatic techniques from the ZXW-calculus.</description><author>Mark Koch</author><pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/koch-thesis.pdf</guid></item><item><title> Experimental Comparison of Ansatze for Quantum Natural Language Processing</title><link>https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/khatri-thesis.pdf</link><description>The DisCoCat model of natural language is a framework which serves as the foundation for several contemporary experiments in Quantum Natural Language Processing (QNLP). In this model, sentences are represented as string diagrams which compose the meaning of the entire sentence from the meaning of each word. An essential step in performing QNLP tasks is converting DisCoCat string diagrams into quantum circuits, through a mapping known as an ansatz. While several ansätze have been studied in the broader quantum machine learning literature, no comparative study of ansätze exists for the specific case of QNLP models. In this work, we implement multiple ansätze and compare their performance on a variety of QNLP tasks. In doing so, the first experimental results for a QNLP model applied to the paraphrase identification task are presented. We propose a novel approach to overcome the out-of-vocabulary problem faced by contemporary QNLP models, and demonstrate that our proposed method outperforms naive approaches by a significant margin. Further, experimental results relating to the barren plateau phenomenon in quantum machine learning are provided. We present evidence suggesting that circuits derived from DisCoCat string diagrams for binary classification tasks are no more susceptible to the barren plateau problem than regular quantum machine learning circuits.</description><author>Nikhil Khatri</author><pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/khatri-thesis.pdf</guid></item><item><title>Quantum Circuit Optimisation Through Stabiliser Reduction of Pauli Exponentials</title><link>https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/cole-thesis.pdf</link><description>Quantum circuits require careful and in-depth optimisation to be run on existing quantum computers. This project investigates the application of the Product Rotation Lemma, introduced by Will Simmons in [32], as a tool for general circuit optimisation. These optimisations exploit the initial state information to identify redundancies in the circuit. This project delves into the lemma’s applications for the Clifford-Pauli-Exponential form and its synthesis alongside the practical applications of this theory. The main contributions from this project are (1) the Pauli DAG Merging Theorem and its surrounding theory that gives simple necessary, and sufficient conditions for applying the Product Rotation Lemma in a strictly beneficial way and (2) providing results strongly indicating the feasibility of the techniques presented here as tools to be used in generic compilation procedures. This report provides proof of the novel theory coming out of this project, alongside a design and implementation of an end-to-end QASM-to-QASM compiler using staq as the base [3]. This compiler is very efficient on large circuits and provides CX count, and depth reductions of up to 42% after existing methods are applied.</description><author>Oliver Cole</author><pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/cole-thesis.pdf</guid></item><item><title>Graphical Stabilizer Decompositions For Counting Problems</title><link>https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/laakkonen-thesis.pdf</link><description>Building on the work of de Beaudrap, Kissinger, and Meichanetzidis [dKM21], in this dissertation, we examine the relationship between #SAT and the ZH calculus. We outline their reduction from #SAT to evaluating ZH diagrams, which shows that evaluating ZH diagrams is #P-hard, and we extend this to show that evaluating diagrams in certain fragments of the ZH calculus, is $FP^#P$-complete. In particular, we show this holds for diagrams where all H-boxes have labels in $ℚ[i,\sqrt2]$, which includes both the Clifford+T and Toffoli-Hadamard fragments natively [BKM+21]. We show the action of the DPLL algorithm [DLL62] for SAT and its derivative CDP [BL99] for #SAT in terms of ZH-diagrams, and use diagrammatic methods to extend CDP to treat variables and clauses equally. Combining this with an algorithm for #2SAT by Wahlström [Wah08], we derive novel upper bounds in terms of clauses and variables for #kSAT that are independent of $k$, and better than brute-force for small clause densities of $\fracmn &lt; 2.25$.
This improves on the upper bound of Dubois [Dub91] whenever $\fracmn &lt; 1.858$ and $k ≥ 4$, and the average-case analysis by Williams [Wil04] whenever $\fracmn &lt; 1.217$ and $k ≥ 6$. We also obtain an unconditional upper bound of
$O∗(1.88m)$ for #4SAT in terms of clauses only.
Finally, we find novel stabilizer decompositions of certain ZH-diagrams and use this to adapt the algorithm of Kissinger and van de Wetering [Kv21] [KvV22] for evaluating ZX-diagrams using stabilizer decompositions to evaluate #2SAT instances. We examine the effect of different decomposition strategies on its runtime but conclude that the algorithm as given is not
effective, and suggest avenues for further improvement.</description><author>Tuomas Laakkonen</author><pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/laakkonen-thesis.pdf</guid></item><item><title>Barren plateaus in quantum tensor network optimization</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2209.00292</link><description>We analyze the barren plateau phenomenon in the variational optimization of quantum circuits inspired by matrix product states (qMPS), tree tensor networks (qTTN), and the multiscale entanglement renormalization ansatz (qMERA). We consider as the cost function the expectation value of a Hamiltonian that is a sum of local terms. For randomly chosen variational parameters we show that the variance of the cost function gradient decreases exponentially with the distance of a Hamiltonian term from the canonical centre in the quantum tensor network. Therefore, as a function of qubit count, for qMPS most gradient variances decrease exponentially and for qTTN as well as qMERA they decrease polynomially. We also show that the calculation of these gradients is exponentially more efficient on a classical computer than on a quantum computer.</description><author>Enrique Cervero Martín, Kirill Plekhanov and Michael Lubasch</author><pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2209.00292</guid></item><item><title>[Video] How to sum and exponentiate Hamiltonians in ZXW calculus &amp;#127909;</title><link>https://youtu.be/_s2pOcrdmig?t=1347</link><description>How to sum and exponentiate Hamiltonians in ZXW calculus</description><author>Quanlong Wang Razin Shaikh and Richie Yeung</author><pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://youtu.be/_s2pOcrdmig?t=1347</guid></item></channel></rss>