<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Nov 2021 19:10:58 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Spin-networks in the ZX-calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.03114</link><description>The ZX-calculus, and the variant we consider in this paper (ZXH-calculus), are formal diagrammatic languages for qubit quantum computing. We show that it can also be used to describe SU(2) representation theory. To achieve this, we first recall the definition of Yutsis diagrams, a standard graphical calculus used in quantum chemistry and quantum gravity, which captures the main features of SU(2) representation theory. Second, we show precisely how it embed within Penrose's binor calculus. Third, we subsume both calculus into ZXH-diagrams. In the process we show how the SU(2) invariance of Wigner symbols is trivially provable in the ZXH-calculus. Additionally, we show how we can explicitly diagrammatically calculate 3jm, 4jm and 6j symbols. It has long been thought that quantum gravity should be closely aligned to quantum information theory. In this paper, we present a way in which this connection can be made exact, by writing the spin-networks of loop quantum gravity (LQG) in the ZX-diagrammatic language of quantum computation.</description><author>Richard D. P. East, Pierre Martin-Dussaud and John van de Wetering</author><pubDate>Thu, 04 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.03114</guid></item><item><title>Representing Matrices Using Algebraic ZX-calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.06898</link><description>Elementary matrices play an important role in linear algebra applications. In this paper, we represent all the elementary matrices of size 2^m\times 2^m using algebraic ZX-calculus. Then we show their properties on inverses and transpose using rewriting rules of ZX-calculus. As a consequence, we are able to depict any matrices of size 2^m\times 2^n by string diagrams without resort to a diagrammatic normal form for matrices as shown in [Wang 2020]. By doing so we pave the way towards visualising by string diagrams important matrix technologies deployed in AI especially machine learning.</description><author>Quanlong Wang</author><pubDate>Wed, 13 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.06898</guid></item><item><title>A non-anyonic qudit ZW-calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2109.11285</link><description>ZW-calculus is a useful graphical language for pure qubit quantum computing. It is via the translation of the completeness of ZW-calculus that the first proof of completeness of ZX-calculus was obtained. A d-level generalisation of qubit ZW-calculus (anyonic qudit ZW-calculus) has been given in i̧teamar which is universal for pure qudit quantum computing. However, the interpretation of the W spider in this type of ZW-calculus has so-called q-binomial coefficients involved, thus makes computation quite complicated. In this paper, we give a new type of qudit ZW-calculus which has generators and rewriting rules similar to that of the qubit ZW-calculus. Especially, the Z spider is exactly the same as that of the qudit ZX-calculus as given in \ţewangqufinite, and the new W spider has much simpler interpretation as a linear map. Furthermore, we establish a translation between this qudit ZW-calculus and the qudit ZX-calculus which is universal as shown in \cȩwangqufinite, therefore this qudit ZW-calculus is also universal for pure qudit quantum computing.</description><author>Quanlong Wang</author><pubDate>Thu, 23 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2109.11285</guid></item><item><title>Relating Measurement Patterns to Circuits via Pauli Flow</title><link>https://dx.doi.org/10.4204/EPTCS.343.4</link><description>The one-way model of Measurement-Based Quantum Computing and the gate-based circuit model give two different presentations of how quantum computation can be performed. There are known methods for converting any gate-based quantum circuit into a one-way computation, whereas the reverse is only efficient given some constraints on the structure of the measurement pattern. Causal flow and generalised flow have already been shown as sufficient, with efficient algorithms for identifying these properties and performing the circuit extraction. Pauli flow is a weaker set of conditions that extends generalised flow to use the knowledge that some vertices are measured in a Pauli basis. In this paper, we show that Pauli flow can similarly be identified efficiently and that any measurement pattern whose underlying graph admits a Pauli flow can be efficiently transformed into a gate-based circuit without using ancilla qubits. We then use this relationship to derive simulation results for the effects of graph-theoretic rewrites in the ZX-calculus using a more circuit-like data structure we call the Pauli Dependency DAG.</description><author>Will Simmons</author><pubDate>Mon, 13 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.05654</guid></item><item><title>Simulating quantum circuits with ZX-calculus reduced stabiliser decompositions</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2109.01076</link><description>We introduce an enhanced technique for strong classical simulation of quantum circuits which combines the `sum-of-stabilisers' method with an automated simplification strategy based on the ZX-calculus. Recently it was shown that quantum circuits can be classically simulated by expressing the non-stabiliser gates in a circuit as magic state injections and decomposing them in chunks of 2-6 states at a time, obtaining sums of (efficiently-simulable) stabiliser states with many fewer terms than the naive approach. We adapt these techniques from the original setting of Clifford circuits with magic state injection to generic ZX-diagrams and show that, by interleaving this "chunked" decomposition with a ZX-calculus-based simplification strategy, we can obtain stabiliser decompositions that are many orders of magnitude smaller than existing approaches. We illustrate this technique to perform exact norm calculations (and hence strong simulation) on the outputs of random 50- and 100-qubit Clifford+T circuits with up to 70 T-gates as well as a family of hidden shift circuits previously considered by Bravyi and Gosset with over 1000 T-gates.</description><author>Aleks Kissinger and John van de Wetering</author><pubDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2109.01076</guid></item><item><title>Quantum Multiple-Valued Decision Diagrams in Graphical Calculi</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2107.01186</link><description>Graphical calculi such as the ZH-calculus are powerful tools in the study and analysis of quantum processes, with links to other models of quantum computation such as quantum circuits, measurement-based computing, etc.   A somewhat compact but systematic way to describe a quantum process is through the use of quantum multiple-valued decision diagrams (QMDDs), which have already been used for the synthesis of quantum circuits as well as for verification.   We show in this paper how to turn a QMDD into an equivalent ZH-diagram, and vice-versa, and show how reducing a QMDD translates in the ZH-Calculus, hence allowing tools from one formalism to be used into the other.</description><author>Renaud Vilmart</author><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jul 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2107.01186</guid></item><item><title>Quantum double aspects of surface code models</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2107.04411</link><description>We revisit the Kitaev model for fault tolerant quantum computing on a square lattice with underlying quantum double $D(G)$ symmetry, where $G$ is a finite group. We provide projection operators for its quasiparticles content as irreducible representations of $D(G)$ and combine this with $D(G)$-bimodule properties of open ribbon excitation spaces $L(s_0,s_1)$ to show how open ribbons can be used to teleport information between their endpoints $s_0,s_1$. We give a self-contained account that builds on earlier work but emphasises applications to quantum computing as surface code theory, including gates on $D(S_3)$. We show how the theory reduces to a simpler theory for toric codes in the case of $D( \Bbb Z_n)≅ \Bbb C\Bbb Z_n^2$, including toric ribbon operators and their braiding. In the other direction, we show how our constructions generalise to $D(H)$ models based on a finite-dimensional Hopf algebra $H$, including site actions of $D(H)$ and partial results on ribbon equivariance even when the Hopf algebra is not semisimple.</description><author>Alexander Cowtan and Shahn Majid</author><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jun 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2107.04411</guid></item><item><title>The role of compositionality in constructing complementary classical structures within qubit systems</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2105.11966</link><description>Observables in a quantum system, represented by a Hilbert space, are given by the orthogonal bases of the aforementioned Hilbert space. Categorical Quantum Mechanics provides further abstraction of such observables, allowing for a diagrammatic representation of measurements that extends to quantum processes. Our research studies this abstraction of observables, which has been dubbed as classical structures, in a subtheory of quantum mechanics which focuses on qubit systems (or 2-dimensional quantum system and its composites). We have constructed a procedure that takes the complementary classical structures of a single qubit system and compose them separably via the Kronecker product or 'entangle' them via Bell states to obtain complementary classical structures in n-qubit systems. In this present work, we apply our procedure to two qubit and three qubit systems as examples. Then, using rewriting rules of ZX-calculus and tools in graph theory, we searched for maximal complete sets of mutually complementary classical structures (the categorical counterpart of mutually unbiased bases) among our constructed composite classical structures. For two qubits, we found 13 maximal complete sets of mutually complementary classical structures, and for three qubits, we found 32,448 maximal complete sets of mutually complementary classical structures.</description><author>Siti Aqilah Binti Muhamad Rasat</author><pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2105.11966</guid></item><item><title>A Graphical Calculus for Lagrangian Relations</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2105.06244</link><description>Symplectic vector spaces are the phase space of linear mechanical systems. The symplectic form describes, for example, the relation between position and momentum as well as current and voltage. The category of linear Lagrangian relations between symplectic vector spaces is a symmetric monoidal subcategory of relations which gives a semantics for the evolution -- and more generally linear constraints on the evolution -- of various physical systems.   We give a new presentation of the category of Lagrangian relations over an arbitrary field as a `doubled' category of linear relations. More precisely, we show that it arises as a variation of Selinger's CPM construction applied to linear relations, where the covariant orthogonal complement functor plays of the role of conjugation. Furthermore, for linear relations over prime fields, this corresponds exactly to the CPM construction for a suitable choice of dagger. We can furthermore extend this construction by a single affine shift operator to obtain a category of affine Lagrangian relations. Using this new presentation, we prove the equivalence of the prop of affine Lagrangian relations with the prop of qudit stabilizer theory in odd prime dimensions. We hence obtain a unified graphical language for several disparate process theories, including electrical circuits, Spekkens' toy theory, and odd-prime-dimensional stabilizer quantum circuits.</description><author>Cole Comfort and Aleks Kissinger</author><pubDate>Thu, 13 May 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2105.06244</guid></item><item><title>[Video] Vanishing 2-qubit gates with non-simplification ZX-rules &amp;#127909;</title><link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tUIcqXKEFhk</link><description>Traditional quantum circuit optimization is performed directly at the circuit level. Alternatively, a quantum circuit can be translated to a ZX-diagram which can be simplified using the rules of the ZX-calculus, after which a simplified circuit can be extracted. However, the best-known extraction procedures can drastically increase the number of 2-qubit gates. In this work, we take advantage of the fact that local changes in a ZX-diagram can drastically affect the complexity of the extracted circuit. We use a pair of congruences (i.e., non-simplification rewrite rules) based on the graph-theoretic notions of local complementation and pivoting to generate local variants of a simplified ZX-diagram. We explore the space of equivalent ZX-diagrams generated by these congruences using simulated annealing and genetic algorithms to obtain a simplified circuit with fewer 2-qubit gates.

Our method can reliably outperform state-of-the-art optimization techniques for low-qubit, less than 10 qubit, circuits and serves as a proof-of-concept for a new circuit optimization strategy in the ZX-calculus.
</description><author>Ryan Krueger</author><pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tUIcqXKEFhk</guid></item></channel></rss>