<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2021 12:52:00 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Distributive Laws, Spans and the ZX-Calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2102.04386</link><description>We modularly build increasingly larger fragments of the ZX-calculus by modularly adding new generators and relations, at each point, giving some concrete semantics in terms of some category of spans. This is performed using Lack's technique of composing props via distributive laws, as well as the technique of pushout cubes of Zanasi. We do this for the fragment of the ZX-calculus with only the black $π$-phase (and no Hadamard gate) as well as well as the fragment which additionally has the and gate as a generator (which is equivalent to the natural number H-box fragment of the ZH calculus). In the former case, we show that this is equivalent to the full subcategory of spans of (possibly empty) free, finite dimensional affine $\mathbb F_2$-vector spaces, where the objects are the non-empty affine vector spaces. In the latter case, we show that this is equivalent to the full subcategory of spans of finite sets where the objects are powers of the two element set. Because these fragments of the ZX-calculus have semantics in terms of full subcategories of categories of spans, they can not be presented by distributive laws over groupoids. Instead, we first construct their subcategories of partial isomorphisms via distributive laws over all isomorphims with subobjects adoined. After which, the full subcategory of spans are obtained by freely adjoining units and counits the the semi-Frobenius structures given by the diagonal and codiagonal maps.</description><author>Cole Comfort</author><pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2102.04386</guid></item><item><title>Construction of classical structures on N qubits by composing diagrammatic eigenbases of Pauli operators</title><link>https://dx.doi.org/10.1063/5.0036992</link><description>Within the framework of Categorical Quantum Mechanics, it was found that orthogonal bases are subsumed by the so called classical structures. So, there must be classical structures which have the eigenbases of the Pauli X,Y and Z operators as their underlying bases. In this article, we propose a procedure for composing these classical structures on a single qubit which produces classical structures on multiple qubits. As a result, we can present orthogonal bases within a multiple qubit system as diagrams which makes explicit the entanglement structure of those bases.</description><author>Aqilah Rasat</author><pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://doi.org/10.1063/5.0036992</guid></item><item><title>Graphical Language with Delayed Trace: Picturing Quantum Computing with Finite Memory</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2102.03133</link><description>Graphical languages, like quantum circuits or ZX-calculus, have been successfully designed to represent (memoryless) quantum computations acting on a finite number of qubits. Meanwhile, delayed traces have been used as a graphical way to represent finite-memory computations on streams, in a classical setting (cartesian data types). We merge those two approaches and describe a general construction that extends any graphical language, equipped with a notion of discarding, to a graphical language of finite memory computations. In order to handle cases like the ZX-calculus, which is complete for post-selected quantum mechanics, we extend the delayed trace formalism beyond the causal case, refining the notion of causality for stream transformers. We design a stream semantics based on stateful morphism sequences and, under some assumptions, show universality and completeness results. Finally, we investigate the links of our framework with previous works on cartesian data types, signal flow graphs, and quantum channels with memories.</description><author>Titouan Carette, Marc de Visme and Simon Perdrix</author><pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2102.03133</guid></item><item><title>Analyzing the barren plateau phenomenon in training quantum neural network with the ZX-calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2102.01828</link><description>In this paper, we propose a general scheme to analyze the barren plateau phenomenon in training quantum neural networks with the ZX-calculus. More precisely, we extend the barren plateaus theorem from unitary 2-design circuits to any parameterized quantum circuits under certain reasonable assumptions. The main technical contribution of this paper is representing certain integrations as ZX-diagrams and computing them with the ZX-calculus. The method is used to analyze four concrete quantum neural networks with different structures. It is shown that, for the hardware efficient ansatz and the MPS-inspired ansatz, there exist barren plateaus, while for the QCNN and the tree tensor network ansatz, there exists no barren plateau.</description><author>Chen Zhao and Xiao-Shan Gao</author><pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2102.01828</guid></item><item><title>Parametrized Quantum Circuits of Synonymous Sentences in Quantum Natural Language Processing</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2102.02204</link><description>In this paper, we develop a compositional vector-based semantics of positive transitive sentences in quantum natural language processing for a non-English language, i.e. Persian, to compare the parametrized quantum circuits of two synonymous sentences in two languages, English and Persian. By considering grammar+meaning of a transitive sentence, we translate DisCoCat diagram via ZX-calculus into quantum circuit form. Also, we use a bigraph method to rewrite DisCoCat diagram and turn into quantum circuit in the semantic side.</description><author>Mina Abbaszadeh, S. Shahin Mousavi and Vahid Salari</author><pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2102.02204</guid></item><item><title>Quantum Theory from Principles, Quantum Software from Diagrams</title><link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2101.03608</link><description>This thesis consists of two parts. The first part is about how quantum theory can be recovered from first principles, while the second part is about the application of diagrammatic reasoning, specifically the ZX-calculus, to practical problems in quantum computing. The main results of the first part include a reconstruction of quantum theory from principles related to properties of sequential measurement and a reconstruction based on properties of pure maps and the mathematics of effectus theory. It also includes a detailed study of JBW-algebras, a type of infinite-dimensional Jordan algebra motivated by von Neumann algebras. In the second part we find a new model for measurement-based quantum computing, study how measurement patterns in the one-way model can be simplified and find a new algorithm for extracting a unitary circuit from such patterns. We use these results to develop a circuit optimisation strategy that leads to a new normal form for Clifford circuits and reductions in the T-count of Clifford+T circuits.</description><author>John van de Wetering</author><pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2101.03608</guid></item><item><title>ZX-calculus for the working quantum computer scientist</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.13966</link><description>The ZX-calculus is a graphical language for reasoning about quantum computation that has recently seen an increased usage in a variety of areas such as quantum circuit optimisation, surface codes and lattice surgery, measurement-based quantum computation, and quantum foundations. The first half of this review gives a gentle introduction to the ZX-calculus suitable for those familiar with the basics of quantum computing. The aim here is to make the reader comfortable enough with the ZX-calculus that they could use it in their daily work for small computations on quantum circuits and states. The latter sections give a condensed overview of the literature on the ZX-calculus. We discuss Clifford computation and graphically prove the Gottesman-Knill theorem, we discuss a recently introduced extension of the ZX-calculus that allows for convenient reasoning about Toffoli gates, and we discuss the recent completeness theorems for the ZX-calculus that show that, in principle, all reasoning about quantum computation can be done using ZX-diagrams. Additionally, we discuss the categorical and algebraic origins of the ZX-calculus and we discuss several extensions of the language which can represent mixed states, measurement, classical control and higher-dimensional qudits.</description><author>John van de Wetering</author><pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.13966</guid></item><item><title>A note on diagonal gates in SZX-calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.09540</link><description>This note describes how the scalable ZXH calculus can be used to represent in a compact way the quantum gates that are diagonal in the computational basis. This includes controlled and multi-controlled Z gates, their generalizations, respectively graph and hypergraph operators, and also phase gadgets.</description><author>Titouan Carette</author><pubDate>Thu, 17 Dec 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.09540</guid></item><item><title>Constructing quantum circuits with global gates</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.09061</link><description>There are various gate sets that can be used to describe a quantum computation. A particularly popular gate set in the literature on quantum computing consists of arbitrary single-qubit gates and 2-qubit CNOT gates. A CNOT gate is however not always the natural multi-qubit interaction that can be implemented on a given physical quantum computer, necessitating a compilation step that transforms these CNOT gates to the native gate set. A particularly interesting case where compilation is necessary is for ion trap quantum computers, where the natural entangling operation can act on more than 2 qubits and can even act globally on all qubits at once. This calls for an entirely different approach to constructing efficient circuits. In this paper we study the problem of converting a given circuit that uses 2-qubit gates to one that uses global gates. Our three main contributions are as follows. First, we find an efficient algorithm for transforming an arbitrary circuit consisting of Clifford gates and arbitrary phase gates into a circuit consisting of single-qubit gates and a number of global interactions proportional to the number of non-Clifford phases present in the original circuit. Second, we find a general strategy to transform a global gate that targets all qubits into one that targets only a subset of the qubits. This approach scales linearly with the number of qubits that are not targeted, in contrast to the exponential scaling reported in (Maslov &amp; Nam, N. J. Phys. 2018). Third, we improve on the number of global gates required to synthesise an arbitrary n-qubit Clifford circuit from the 12n-18 reported in (Maslov &amp; Nam, N. J. Phys. 2018) to 6n-8.</description><author>John van de Wetering</author><pubDate>Wed, 16 Dec 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.09061</guid></item><item><title>Foundations for Near-Term Quantum Natural Language Processing</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.03755</link><description>We provide conceptual and mathematical foundations for near-term quantum natural language processing (QNLP), and do so in quantum computer scientist friendly terms. We opted for an expository presentation style, and provide references for supporting empirical evidence and formal statements concerning mathematical generality.   We recall how the quantum model for natural language that we employ canonically combines linguistic meanings with rich linguistic structure, most notably grammar. In particular, the fact that it takes a quantum-like model to combine meaning and structure, establishes QNLP as quantum-native, on par with simulation of quantum systems. Moreover, the now leading Noisy Intermediate-Scale Quantum (NISQ) paradigm for encoding classical data on quantum hardware, variational quantum circuits, makes NISQ exceptionally QNLP-friendly: linguistic structure can be encoded as a free lunch, in contrast to the apparently exponentially expensive classical encoding of grammar.   Quantum speed-up for QNLP tasks has already been established in previous work with Will Zeng. Here we provide a broader range of tasks which all enjoy the same advantage.   Diagrammatic reasoning is at the heart of QNLP. Firstly, the quantum model interprets language as quantum processes via the diagrammatic formalism of categorical quantum mechanics. Secondly, these diagrams are via ZX-calculus translated into quantum circuits. Parameterisations of meanings then become the circuit variables to be learned.   Our encoding of linguistic structure within quantum circuits also embodies a novel approach for establishing word-meanings that goes beyond the current standards in mainstream AI, by placing linguistic structure at the heart of Wittgenstein's meaning-is-context.</description><author>Bob Coecke, Giovanni de Felice, Konstantinos Meichanetzidis and Alexis Toumi</author><pubDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2012.03755</guid></item></channel></rss>