<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2022 17:42:31 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Addition and Differentiation of ZX-diagrams</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2202.11386</link><description>The ZX-calculus is a powerful framework for reasoning in quantum computing. It provides in particular a compact representation of matrices of interests. A peculiar property of the ZX-calculus is the absence of a formal sum allowing the linear combinations of arbitrary ZX-diagrams. The universality of the formalism guarantees however that for any two ZX-diagrams, the sum of their interpretations can be represented by a ZX-diagram. We introduce a general, inductive definition of the addition of ZX-diagrams, relying on the construction of controlled diagrams. Based on this addition technique, we provide an inductive differentiation of ZX-diagrams.   Indeed, given a ZX-diagram with variables in the description of its angles, one can differentiate the diagram according to one of these variables. Differentiation is ubiquitous in quantum mechanics and quantum computing (e.g. for solving optimization problems). Technically, differentiation of ZX-diagrams is strongly related to summation as witnessed by the product rules.   We also introduce an alternative, non inductive, differentiation technique rather based on the isolation of the variables. Finally, we apply our results to deduce a diagram for an Ising Hamiltonian.</description><author>Emmanuel Jeandel, Simon Perdrix and Margarita Veshchezerova</author><pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2202.11386</guid></item><item><title>Classical simulation of quantum circuits with partial and graphical stabiliser decompositions</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2202.09202</link><description>Recent developments in classical simulation of quantum circuits make use of clever decompositions of chunks of magic states into sums of efficiently simulable stabiliser states. We show here how, by considering certain non-stabiliser entangled states which have more favourable decompositions, we can speed up these simulations. This is made possible by using the ZX-calculus, which allows us to easily find instances of these entangled states in the simplified diagram representing the quantum circuit to be simulated. We additionally find a new technique of partial stabiliser decompositions that allow us to trade magic states for stabiliser terms. With this technique we require only $2^α t$ stabiliser terms, where $α≈ 0.396$, to simulate a circuit with T-count $t$. This matches the $α$ found by Qassim et al., but whereas they only get this scaling in the asymptotic limit, ours applies for a circuit of any size. Our method builds upon a recently proposed scheme for simulation combining stabiliser decompositions and optimisation strategies implemented in the software QuiZX. With our techniques we manage to reliably simulate 50-qubit 1400 T-count hidden shift circuits in a couple of minutes on a consumer laptop.</description><author>Aleks Kissinger, John van de Wetering and Renaud Vilmart</author><pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2202.09202</guid></item><item><title>Circuit Extraction for ZX-diagrams can be #P-hard</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2202.09194</link><description>The ZX-calculus is a graphical language for reasoning about quantum computation using ZX-diagrams, a certain flexible generalisation of quantum circuits that can be used to represent linear maps from $m$ to $n$ qubits for any $m,n ≥ 0$. Some applications for the ZX-calculus, such as quantum circuit optimisation and synthesis, rely on being able to efficiently translate a ZX-diagram back into a quantum circuit of comparable size. While several sufficient conditions are known for describing families of ZX-diagrams that can be efficiently transformed back into circuits, it has previously been conjectured that the general problem of circuit extraction is hard. That is, that it should not be possible to efficiently convert an arbitrary ZX-diagram describing a unitary linear map into an equivalent quantum circuit. In this paper we prove this conjecture by showing that the circuit extraction problem is #P-hard, and so is itself at least as hard as strong simulation of quantum circuits. In addition to our main hardness result, which relies specifically on the circuit representation, we give a representation-agnostic hardness result. Namely, we show that any oracle that takes as input a ZX-diagram description of a unitary and produces samples of the output of the associated quantum computation enables efficient probabilistic solutions to NP-complete problems.</description><author>Niel de Beaudrap, Aleks Kissinger and John van de Wetering</author><pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2202.09194</guid></item><item><title>Differentiating and Integrating ZX Diagrams</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.13250</link><description>ZX-calculus has proved to be a useful tool for quantum technology with a wide range of successful applications. Most of these applications are of an algebraic nature. However, other tasks that involve differentiation and integration remain unreachable with current ZX techniques. Here we elevate ZX to an analytical perspective by realising differentiation and integration entirely within the framework of ZX-calculus. We explicitly illustrate the new analytic framework of ZX-calculus by applying it in context of quantum machine learning.</description><author>Quanlong Wang and Richie Yeung</author><pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2201.13250</guid></item><item><title>Wielding the ZX-calculus, Flexsymmetry, Mixed States, and Scalable Notations</title><link>https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/tel-03468027/document</link><description>My first contribution is to propose a formalisation of this property through the notion of flexsymmetry in Chapter 5, it relies on the notion of paradigm introduced in Chapter 4. This equation called the bialgebra rule and making two spiders interact is the key ingredient in the definition of Z*-algebras in Chapter 6 where it is shown that the red and green spiders are not the only ones following this pattern. The introduction of Z*-algebras and the classification of all their models in qubits is the second contribution of this thesis. There are essentially three such structures for qubits, corresponding to the ZX-calculus, ZH-calculus, and ZW-calculus. Similar behaviour can also appear in other settings, as in the graphical linear algebra introduced in Chapter 7. All those calculi can then be used to represent quantum algorithms. But there are two obstacles. First, those algorithms can involve interactions with the non-quantum world that require a broader model of computation allowing classical behaviours alongside quantum ones.
This is called mixed state quantum mechanics and a way to extend quantum graphical languages to this setting is presented in Chapter 8. The extension of ZX-calculus to mixed-state quantum mechanics is the third contribution presented in this thesis. A second obstacle is the fact that a quantum algorithm is defined by a uniform family of circuits, one for each possible size of the input. The scalable notations presented in Chapter 9 allow to handle such families, completing the toolbox necessary to calmly approach quantum algorithm graphically. The scalable notations are the fourth and last theoretical contribution of this thesis.
All those methods can be used to graphically prove the correction of quantum algorithms. Examples are provided in Chapter 10, which concludes the thesis.</description><author>Titouan Carette</author><pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/tel-03468027/document</guid></item><item><title>Spin-networks in the ZX-calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.03114</link><description>The ZX-calculus, and the variant we consider in this paper (ZXH-calculus), are formal diagrammatic languages for qubit quantum computing. We show that it can also be used to describe SU(2) representation theory. To achieve this, we first recall the definition of Yutsis diagrams, a standard graphical calculus used in quantum chemistry and quantum gravity, which captures the main features of SU(2) representation theory. Second, we show precisely how it embed within Penrose's binor calculus. Third, we subsume both calculus into ZXH-diagrams. In the process we show how the SU(2) invariance of Wigner symbols is trivially provable in the ZXH-calculus. Additionally, we show how we can explicitly diagrammatically calculate 3jm, 4jm and 6j symbols. It has long been thought that quantum gravity should be closely aligned to quantum information theory. In this paper, we present a way in which this connection can be made exact, by writing the spin-networks of loop quantum gravity (LQG) in the ZX-diagrammatic language of quantum computation.</description><author>Richard D. P. East, Pierre Martin-Dussaud and John van de Wetering</author><pubDate>Thu, 04 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2111.03114</guid></item><item><title>Representing Matrices Using Algebraic ZX-calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.06898</link><description>Elementary matrices play an important role in linear algebra applications. In this paper, we represent all the elementary matrices of size 2^m\times 2^m using algebraic ZX-calculus. Then we show their properties on inverses and transpose using rewriting rules of ZX-calculus. As a consequence, we are able to depict any matrices of size 2^m\times 2^n by string diagrams without resort to a diagrammatic normal form for matrices as shown in [Wang 2020]. By doing so we pave the way towards visualising by string diagrams important matrix technologies deployed in AI especially machine learning.</description><author>Quanlong Wang</author><pubDate>Wed, 13 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2110.06898</guid></item><item><title>Optimization Approaches for Quantum Circuits using ZX-calculus</title><link>https://www.mnm-team.org/pub/Diplomarbeiten/stau21/PDF-Version/stau21.pdf</link><description>This work focuses on quantum circuit optimization using the ZX-calculus, a recently developed graphical language designed to simplify reasoning about quantum systems. Quantum circuits can be optimized in an intuitive and efficient way by transforming them to equivalent ZX-diagrams and using rules of the ZX-calculus for diagram simplification. However, some rules can modify ZX-diagrams in such a way that the re-extraction of a quantum circuit is no longer possible. Moreover, rules that simplify ZX-diagrams can still increase the size of the underlying circuits. Due to these problems, most of the existing ZXcalculus based optimization approaches become inefficient with increasing quantum circuit complexity. In our work we develop different strategies to improve those approaches. In particular, we introduce heuristics to estimate the optimization benefit gained by certain ZX-rules. This allows treating ZX-diagram simplification as a classical search problem where heuristics can be applied to guide the sequence of rule applications towards minimal circuits. We implement different heuristic-based algorithms like greedy search, random search and simulated annealing in the open-source library PyZX where we test them against existing strategies on circuits of variant size. The results show that using heuristics in diagram simplification often leads to better overall optimization results, especially when optimizing large and complex quantum circuits. Our algorithms can be further improved in several aspects like runtime or consideration of hardware topology.
</description><author>Korbinian Staudacher</author><pubDate>Thu, 30 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.mnm-team.org/pub/Diplomarbeiten/stau21/PDF-Version/stau21.pdf</guid></item><item><title>A non-anyonic qudit ZW-calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2109.11285</link><description>ZW-calculus is a useful graphical language for pure qubit quantum computing. It is via the translation of the completeness of ZW-calculus that the first proof of completeness of ZX-calculus was obtained. A d-level generalisation of qubit ZW-calculus (anyonic qudit ZW-calculus) has been given in i̧teamar which is universal for pure qudit quantum computing. However, the interpretation of the W spider in this type of ZW-calculus has so-called q-binomial coefficients involved, thus makes computation quite complicated. In this paper, we give a new type of qudit ZW-calculus which has generators and rewriting rules similar to that of the qubit ZW-calculus. Especially, the Z spider is exactly the same as that of the qudit ZX-calculus as given in \ţewangqufinite, and the new W spider has much simpler interpretation as a linear map. Furthermore, we establish a translation between this qudit ZW-calculus and the qudit ZX-calculus which is universal as shown in \cȩwangqufinite, therefore this qudit ZW-calculus is also universal for pure qudit quantum computing.</description><author>Quanlong Wang</author><pubDate>Thu, 23 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2109.11285</guid></item><item><title>Relating Measurement Patterns to Circuits via Pauli Flow</title><link>https://dx.doi.org/10.4204/EPTCS.343.4</link><description>The one-way model of Measurement-Based Quantum Computing and the gate-based circuit model give two different presentations of how quantum computation can be performed. There are known methods for converting any gate-based quantum circuit into a one-way computation, whereas the reverse is only efficient given some constraints on the structure of the measurement pattern. Causal flow and generalised flow have already been shown as sufficient, with efficient algorithms for identifying these properties and performing the circuit extraction. Pauli flow is a weaker set of conditions that extends generalised flow to use the knowledge that some vertices are measured in a Pauli basis. In this paper, we show that Pauli flow can similarly be identified efficiently and that any measurement pattern whose underlying graph admits a Pauli flow can be efficiently transformed into a gate-based circuit without using ancilla qubits. We then use this relationship to derive simulation results for the effects of graph-theoretic rewrites in the ZX-calculus using a more circuit-like data structure we call the Pauli Dependency DAG.</description><author>Will Simmons</author><pubDate>Mon, 13 Sep 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.05654</guid></item></channel></rss>