<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2022 15:59:16 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>A Graphical #SAT Algorithm for Formulae with Small Clause Density</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.08048</link><description>We study the counting version of the Boolean satisfiability problem #SAT using the ZH-calculus, a graphical language originally introduced to reason about quantum circuits. Using this we find a natural extension of #SAT which we call $#SAT_±$, where variables are additionally labeled by phases, which is GapP-complete. Using graphical reasoning, we find a reduction from #SAT to $#2SAT_±$ in the ZH-calculus. We observe that the DPLL algorithm for #2SAT can be adapted to $#2SAT_±$ directly and hence that Wahlstrom's $O^*(1.2377^n)$ upper bound applies to $#2SAT_±$ as well. Combining this with our reduction from #SAT to $#2SAT_±$ gives us novel upper bounds in terms of clauses and variables that are better than $O^*(2^n)$ for small clause densities of $\fracmn &lt; 2.25$. This is to our knowledge the first non-trivial upper bound for #SAT that is independent of clause size. Our algorithm improves on Dubois' upper bound for $#kSAT$ whenever $\fracmn &lt; 1.85$ and $k ≥ 4$, and the Williams' average-case analysis whenever $\fracmn &lt; 1.21$ and $k ≥ 6$. We also obtain an unconditional upper bound of $O^*(1.88^m)$ for $#4SAT$ in terms of clauses only, and find an improved bound on $#3SAT$ for $1.2577 &lt; \fracmn łeq \frac73$. Our results demonstrate that graphical reasoning can lead to new algorithmic insights, even outside the domain of quantum computing that the calculus was intended for.</description><author>Tuomas Laakkonen, Konstantinos Meichanetzidis and John van de Wetering</author><pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.08048</guid></item><item><title>How to sum and exponentiate Hamiltonians in ZXW calculus</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.04462</link><description>This paper develops practical summation techniques in ZXW calculus to reason about quantum dynamics, such as unitary time evolution. First we give a direct representation of a wide class of sums of linear operators, including arbitrary qubits Hamiltonians, in ZXW calculus. As an application, we demonstrate the linearity of the Schrödinger equation and give a diagrammatic representation of the Hamiltonian in Greene-Diniz et al (Gabriel, 2022), which is the first paper that models carbon capture using quantum computing. We then use the Cayley-Hamilton theorem to show in principle how to exponentiate arbitrary qubits Hamiltonians in ZXW calculus. Finally, we develop practical techniques and show how to do Taylor expansion and Trotterization diagrammatically for Hamiltonian simulation. This sets up the framework for using ZXW calculus to the problems in quantum chemistry and condensed matter physics.</description><author>Razin A. Shaikh, Quanlong Wang and Richie Yeung</author><pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.04462</guid></item><item><title>Quantum computation on a 19-qubit wide 2d nearest neighbour qubit array</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.01550</link><description>In this paper, we explore the relationship between the width of a qubit lattice constrained in one dimension and physical thresholds for scalable, fault-tolerant quantum computation. To circumvent the traditionally low thresholds of small fixed-width arrays, we deliberately engineer an error bias at the lowest level of encoding using the surface code. We then address this engineered bias at a higher level of encoding using a lattice-surgery surface code bus that exploits this bias, or a repetition code to make logical qubits with unbiased errors out of biased surface code qubits. Arbitrarily low error rates can then be reached by further concatenating with other codes, such as Steane [[7,1,3]] code and the [[15,7,3]] CSS code. This enables a scalable fixed-width quantum computing architecture on a square qubit lattice that is only 19 qubits wide, given physical qubits with an error rate of $8.0\times 10^-4$. This potentially eases engineering issues in systems with fine qubit pitches, such as quantum dots in silicon or gallium arsenide.</description><author>Alexis Shaw, Michael Bremner, Alexandru Paler, Daniel Herr and Simon J. Devitt</author><pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.01550</guid></item><item><title>Active volume: An architecture for efficient fault-tolerant quantum computers with limited non-local connections</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.15465</link><description>In existing general-purpose architectures for surface-code-based fault-tolerant quantum computers, the cost of a quantum computation is determined by the circuit volume, i.e., the number of qubits multiplied by the number of non-Clifford gates. We introduce an architecture using non-2D-local connections in which the cost does not scale with the number of qubits, and instead only with the number of logical operations. Each logical operation has an associated active volume, such that the cost of a quantum computation can be quantified as a sum of active volumes of all operations. For quantum computations with thousands of logical qubits, the active volume can be orders of magnitude lower than the circuit volume. Importantly, the architecture does not require all-to-all connectivity between N logical qubits. Instead, each logical qubit is connected to O(log N) other sites. As an example, we show that, using the same number of logical qubits, a 2048-bit factoring algorithm can be executed 44 times faster than on a general-purpose architecture without non-local connections. With photonic qubits, long-range connections are available and we show how photonic components can be used to construct a fusion-based active-volume quantum computer.</description><author>Daniel Litinski and Naomi Nickerson</author><pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.15465</guid></item><item><title>Graphical calculus for Tensor Network Contractions</title><link>https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/raj-thesis.pdf</link><description>Quantum computing is an emerging field of research that harnesses the laws of quantum mechanics to solve computationally hard problems. In addition to developing better and bigger quantum computers, a significant challenge is developing techniques to benchmark these devices. Thus, pushing the barrier of classical simulation goes hand in hand with the development of quantum computers. In this dissertation, we hope to leverage the existing work on quantum graphical languages such as the ZX-calculus to aid one of the most prominent classical simulation tools, tensor network methods. By their very nature, graphical languages have a more modular representation of quantum circuits, which could be optimized using the associated rewrite rules of the calculi. We investigate how effective the existing procedures are at enhancing tensor network contractions and propose new strategies based on our observations. Furthermore, we evaluate our strategies using a variety of circuits, including the Sycamore circuits used by Google to demonstrate quantum supremacy in 2019.</description><author>Snehal Raj</author><pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/raj-thesis.pdf</guid></item><item><title>Topological Quantum Computation Through the Lens of Categorical Quantum Mechanics</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.03855</link><description>Unitary fusion categories formalise the algebraic theory of topological quantum computation. We rectify confusion around a category describing an anyonic theory and a category describing topological quantum computation. We show that the latter is a subcategory of Hilb. We represent elements of the Fibonacci and Ising models, namely the encoding of qubits and the associated braid group representations, with the ZX-calculus and show that in both cases, the Yang-Baxter equation is directly connected to an instance of the P-rule of the ZX-calculus. In the Ising case, this reduces to a familiar rule relating two distinct Euler decompositions of the Hadamard gate as $π/2$ phase rotations, whereas in the Fibonacci case, we give a previously unconsidered exact solution of the P-rule involving the Golden ratio. We demonstrate the utility of these representations by giving graphical derivations of the single-qubit braid equations for Fibonacci anyons and the single- and two-qubit braid equations for Ising anyons.</description><author>Fatimah Rita Ahmadi and Aleks Kissinger</author><pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2211.03855</guid></item><item><title>Cutting-Edge Graphical Stabiliser Decompositions for Classical Simulation of Quantum Circuits</title><link>https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/codsi-thesis.pdf</link><description>The aim of this thesis is to study and improve classical simulation of quan tum circuits with stabiliser decompositions by using the ZX-calculus. We propose more efficient decompositions for a large family of states in addi- tion to integrating graphs cuts to make use of potential low connectivity of ZX-diagrams. We also discovered different heuristics to speed up the simulations. Finally, we implemented our method and compared it with the state-of-the-art on different families of circuits to asses the improvements achieved by our approach.</description><author>Julien Codsi</author><pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/codsi-thesis.pdf</guid></item><item><title>Quantum Machine Learning using the ZXW-Calculus</title><link>https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/koch-thesis.pdf</link><description>The field of quantum machine learning (QML) explores how quantum computers can be used to more efficiently solve machine learning problems. As an application of hybrid quantum-classical algorithms, it promises a potential quantum advantages in the near term. In this thesis, we use the ZXW-calculus to diagrammatically analyse two key problems that QML applications face. First, we discuss algorithms to compute gradients on quantum hardware that are needed to perform gradient-based optimisation for QML. Concretely, we give new diagrammatic proofs of the common 2- and 4-term parameter shift rules used in the literature. Additionally, we derive a novel, generalised parameter shift rule with 2n terms that is applicable to gates that can be represented with n parametrised spiders in the ZXW-calculus. Furthermore, to the best of our knowledge, we give the first proof of a conjecture by Anselmetti et al. by proving a no-go theorem ruling out more efficient alternatives to the 4-term shift rule. Secondly, we analyse the gradient landscape of quantum ans¨atze for barren plateaus using both empirical and analytical techniques. Concretely, we develop a tool that automatically calculates the variance of gradients and use it to detect likely barren plateaus in commonly used quantum ans¨atze. Furthermore, we formally prove the existence or absence of barren plateaus for a selection of ansätze using diagrammatic techniques from the ZXW-calculus.</description><author>Mark Koch</author><pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/koch-thesis.pdf</guid></item><item><title> Experimental Comparison of Ansatze for Quantum Natural Language Processing</title><link>https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/khatri-thesis.pdf</link><description>The DisCoCat model of natural language is a framework which serves as the foundation for several contemporary experiments in Quantum Natural Language Processing (QNLP). In this model, sentences are represented as string diagrams which compose the meaning of the entire sentence from the meaning of each word. An essential step in performing QNLP tasks is converting DisCoCat string diagrams into quantum circuits, through a mapping known as an ansatz. While several ansätze have been studied in the broader quantum machine learning literature, no comparative study of ansätze exists for the specific case of QNLP models. In this work, we implement multiple ansätze and compare their performance on a variety of QNLP tasks. In doing so, the first experimental results for a QNLP model applied to the paraphrase identification task are presented. We propose a novel approach to overcome the out-of-vocabulary problem faced by contemporary QNLP models, and demonstrate that our proposed method outperforms naive approaches by a significant margin. Further, experimental results relating to the barren plateau phenomenon in quantum machine learning are provided. We present evidence suggesting that circuits derived from DisCoCat string diagrams for binary classification tasks are no more susceptible to the barren plateau problem than regular quantum machine learning circuits.</description><author>Nikhil Khatri</author><pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/khatri-thesis.pdf</guid></item><item><title>Quantum Circuit Optimisation Through Stabiliser Reduction of Pauli Exponentials</title><link>https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/cole-thesis.pdf</link><description>Quantum circuits require careful and in-depth optimisation to be run on existing quantum computers. This project investigates the application of the Product Rotation Lemma, introduced by Will Simmons in [32], as a tool for general circuit optimisation. These optimisations exploit the initial state information to identify redundancies in the circuit. This project delves into the lemma’s applications for the Clifford-Pauli-Exponential form and its synthesis alongside the practical applications of this theory. The main contributions from this project are (1) the Pauli DAG Merging Theorem and its surrounding theory that gives simple necessary, and sufficient conditions for applying the Product Rotation Lemma in a strictly beneficial way and (2) providing results strongly indicating the feasibility of the techniques presented here as tools to be used in generic compilation procedures. This report provides proof of the novel theory coming out of this project, alongside a design and implementation of an end-to-end QASM-to-QASM compiler using staq as the base [3]. This compiler is very efficient on large circuits and provides CX count, and depth reductions of up to 42% after existing methods are applied.</description><author>Oliver Cole</author><pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/people/aleks.kissinger/theses/cole-thesis.pdf</guid></item></channel></rss>