<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>ZX-calculus publications</title><link>http://zxcalculus.com/publications.rss</link><description>An up to date list of the newest publications related to the ZX-calculus</description><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 18:56:16 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>rfeed v1.0.0</generator><docs>https://github.com/svpino/rfeed/blob/master/README.md</docs><item><title>Barren plateaus in quantum tensor network optimization</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2209.00292</link><description>We analyze the barren plateau phenomenon in the variational optimization of quantum circuits inspired by matrix product states (qMPS), tree tensor networks (qTTN), and the multiscale entanglement renormalization ansatz (qMERA). We consider as the cost function the expectation value of a Hamiltonian that is a sum of local terms. For randomly chosen variational parameters we show that the variance of the cost function gradient decreases exponentially with the distance of a Hamiltonian term from the canonical centre in the quantum tensor network. Therefore, as a function of qubit count, for qMPS most gradient variances decrease exponentially and for qTTN as well as qMERA they decrease polynomially. We also show that the calculation of these gradients is exponentially more efficient on a classical computer than on a quantum computer.</description><author>Enrique Cervero Martín, Kirill Plekhanov and Michael Lubasch</author><pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2209.00292</guid></item><item><title>[Video] How to sum and exponentiate Hamiltonians in ZXW calculus &amp;#127909;</title><link>https://youtu.be/_s2pOcrdmig?t=1347</link><description>How to sum and exponentiate Hamiltonians in ZXW calculus</description><author>Quanlong Wang Razin Shaikh and Richie Yeung</author><pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://youtu.be/_s2pOcrdmig?t=1347</guid></item><item><title>Equivalence Checking of Quantum Circuits with the ZX-Calculus</title><link>https://dx.doi.org/10.1109/JETCAS.2022.3202204</link><description>As state-of-the-art quantum computers are capable of running increasingly complex algorithms, the need for automated methods to design and test potential applications rises. Equivalence checking of quantum circuits is an important, yet hardly automated, task in the development of the quantum software stack. Recently, new methods have been proposed that tackle this problem from widely different perspectives. One of them is based on the ZX-calculus, a graphical rewriting system for quantum computing. However, the power and capability of this equivalence checking method has barely been explored. The aim of this work is to evaluate the ZX-calculus as a tool for equivalence checking of quantum circuits. To this end, it is demonstrated how the ZX-calculus based approach for equivalence checking can be expanded in order to verify the results of compilation flows and optimizations on quantum circuits. It is also shown that the ZX-calculus based method is not complete–especially for quantum circuits with ancillary qubits. In order to properly evaluate the proposed method, we conduct a detailed case study by comparing it to two other state-of-the-art methods for equivalence checking: one based on path-sums and another based on decision diagrams. The proposed methods have been integrated into the publicly available QCEC tool (https://github.com/cda-tum/qcec) which is part of the Munich Quantum Toolkit (MQT).</description><author>Tom Peham, Lukas Burgholzer and Robert Wille</author><pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/9868772/authors#authors</guid></item><item><title>Equivalence Checking Paradigms in Quantum Circuit Design: A Case Study</title><link>https://dx.doi.org/10.1145/3489517.3530480</link><description>As state-of-the-art quantum computers are capable of running increasingly complex algorithms, the need for automated methods to design and test potential applications rises. Equivalence checking of quantum circuits is an important, yet hardly automated, task in the development of the quantum software stack. Recently, new methods have been proposed that tackle this problem from widely different perspectives. However, there is no established baseline on which to judge current and future progress in equivalence checking of quantum circuits. In order to close this gap, we conduct a detailed case study of two of the most promising equivalence checking methodologies---one based on decision diagrams and one based on the ZX-calculus---and compare their strengths and weaknesses.</description><author>Tom Peham, Lukas Burgholzer and Robert Wille</author><pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://doi.org/10.1145/3489517.3530480</guid></item><item><title>Formal diagrammatic spin physics</title><link>https://tel.archives-ouvertes.fr/tel-03719945</link><description>Diagrams are ubiquitous in physics and have catalysed progress on numerous occasions. From
tensor networks and quantum circuits to Feynman diagrams, there are few areas of physics
that don’t employ some informal pictorial reasoning. These diagrams represent the underlying
mathematical operations and aid physical interpretation, but cannot generally be computed
with directly. In this thesis the ZXH-calculus, a graphical language based on the ZX-calculus,
is offered as a prototype for a formal diagrammatic calculational tool for theoretical physics
involving spin. This extends the ZXH-calculus (and more broadly the ZX family of calculi to
which it belongs) beyond its traditional domain which has largely been dominated by quantum
computing. In order to do this the spin lattices taken from condensed matter physics are studied.
It is also shown how spin-networks of the form often seen as the state-space of loop quantum
gravity (LQG) can diagrammatised along with operators acting on them.
To achieve this a diagrammatic form of SU(2) representation theory is outlined. Following this
in condensed matter a number of results are shown. The 1D AKLT state, a symmetry protected
topological state, is expressed in the ZXH-calculus by developing a representation of spins higher
than 1/2 within the calculus. By exploiting the simplifying power of the ZXH-calculus rules it
is shown how this representation straightforwardly recovers the AKLT matrix-product state
representation, the existence of topologically protected edge states, and the non-vanishing of a
string order parameter. Extending beyond these known properties, the diagrammatic approach
also allows one to analytically derive that the Berry phase of any finite-length 1D AKLT chain
is π. In addition, an alternative proof that the 2D AKLT state on a hexagonal lattice can be
reduced to a graph state, demonstrating that it is a universal quantum computing resource.
Continuing on the theme of condensed matter it is then shown how one can build 2D higher-order
topological phases diagrammatically, which is used to illustrate a symmetry-breaking phase
transition.
Turning to LQG the first step is the analysis of Yutsis diagrams, a standard graphical calculus
used in quantum chemistry and quantum gravity, which captures the main features of SU(2)
representation theory. Second, it is shown how it embeds within Penrose’s binor calculus. The
two are then rewritten as ZXH-diagrams. In the process we show how the SU(2) invariance
of Wigner symbols is trivially provable in the ZXH-calculus. Additionally, we show how we
can explicitly diagrammatically calculate 3jm, 4jm and 6j symbols. It has long been thought
that quantum gravity should be closely aligned to quantum information theory. In this paper,
we present a way in which this connection can be made exact, by writing the spin-networks
of loop quantum gravity in the ZX-diagrammatic language of quantum computation. Finally
after outlining the motivation for considering spin-networks as the quantisation of space, the
geometric operators are discussed, and in specific cases diagrammatic versions of the operators
are provided. More generally what is done here shows a route by which LQG can be interpreted
in quantum informational terms by rewriting its kinematical states as networks of qubits in
ZXH.
In total these results demonstrate that the ZXH-calculus is a powerful language for representing
quantum systems and even allows for the computation on physical states entirely graphically.
Within condensed matter it is hoped this will pave the way to develop more efficient many-body
algorithms and giving a novel diagrammatic perspective on quantum phase transitions. In
LQG it is hoped this re-imagining of its state space will spur further integration of quantum
information and gravity.</description><author>Richard East</author><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://tel.archives-ouvertes.fr/tel-03719945</guid></item><item><title>The Basis of Design Tools for Quantum Computing: Arrays, Decision Diagrams, Tensor Networks, and ZX-Calculus</title><link>https://dx.doi.org/10.1145/3489517.3530627</link><description>Quantum computers promise to efficiently solve important problems classical computers never will. However, in order to capitalize on these prospects, a fully automated quantum software stack needs to be developed. This involves a multitude of complex tasks from the classical simulation of quantum circuits, over their compilation to specific devices, to the verification of the circuits to be executed as well as the obtained results. All of these tasks are highly non-trivial and necessitate efficient data structures to tackle the inherent complexity. Starting from rather straight-forward arrays over decision diagrams (inspired by the design automation community) to tensor networks and the ZX-calculus, various complementary approaches have been proposed. This work provides a look "under the hood" of today's tools and showcases how these means are utilized in them, e.g., for simulation, compilation, and verification of quantum circuits.</description><author>Robert Wille, Lukas Burgholzer, Stefan Hillmich, Thomas Grurl, Alexander Ploier and Tom Peham</author><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">https://doi.org/10.1145/3489517.3530627</guid></item><item><title>Multi-agent blind quantum computation without universal cluster state</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2206.13330</link><description>Blind quantum computation (BQC) protocols enable quantum algorithms to be executed on third-party quantum agents while keeping the data and algorithm confidential. The previous proposals for measurement-based BQC require preparing a highly entangled cluster state. In this paper, we show that such a requirement is not necessary. Our protocol only requires pre-shared bell pairs between delegated quantum agents, and there is no requirement of any classical or quantum information exchange between agents during the execution. Our proposal requires fewer quantum resources than previous proposals by removing the universal cluster state.</description><author>Shuxiang Cao</author><pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2206.13330</guid></item><item><title>A Pair Measurement Surface Code on Pentagons</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2206.12780</link><description>In this paper, I present a way to compile the surface code into two-body parity measurements ("pair measurements"), where the pair measurements run along the edges of a Cairo pentagonal tiling. The resulting circuit improves on prior work by Chao et al. by using fewer pair measurements per four-body stabilizer measurement (5 instead of 6) and fewer time steps per round of stabilizer measurement (6 instead of 10). Using Monte Carlo sampling, I show that these improvements increase the threshold of the surface code when compiling into pair measurements from $≈ 0.2%$ to $≈ 0.4%$, and also that they improve the teraquop footprint at a $0.1%$ physical gate error rate from $≈6000$ qubits to $≈3000$ qubits. However, I also show that Chao et al's construction will have a smaller teraquop footprint for physical gate error rates below $≈ 0.03%$ (due to bidirectional hook errors in my construction). I also compare to the planar honeycomb code, showing that although this work does noticeably reduce the gap between the surface code and the honeycomb code (when compiling into pair measurements), the honeycomb code is still more efficient (threshold $≈ 0.8%$, teraquop footprint at $0.1%$ of $≈ 1000$).</description><author>Craig Gidney</author><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jun 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2206.12780</guid></item><item><title>Annealing optimisation of Mixed ZX Phase Circuits</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2206.11839</link><description>We present a topology-aware optimisation technique for circuits of mixed ZX phase gadgets, based on conjugation by CX gates and simulated annealing.</description><author>Stefano Gogioso and Richie Yeung</author><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2206.11839</guid></item><item><title>Encoding High-level Quantum Programs as SZX-diagrams</title><link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2206.09376</link><description>The Scalable ZX-calculus is a compact graphical language used to reason about linear maps between quantum states. These diagrams have multiple applications, but they frequently have to be constructed in a case-by-case basis. In this work we present a method to encode quantum programs implemented in a fragment of the linear dependently typed Proto-Quipper-D language as families of SZX-diagrams. We define a subset of translatable Proto-Quipper-D programs and show that our procedure is able to encode non-trivial algorithms as diagrams that grow linearly on the size of the program.</description><author>Agustín Borgna and Rafael Romero</author><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="true">http://arxiv.org/abs/2206.09376</guid></item></channel></rss>